<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Grace, mercy, and peace conteining 1 Gods reconciliation to man, 2 Mans reconciliation to God. By Henry Denne an unworthy servant of the Church, ...</title>
            <author>Denne, Henry, 1606 or 7-1660?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175933</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853920</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853920</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19323</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20176)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19323)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1063:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Grace, mercy, and peace conteining 1 Gods reconciliation to man, 2 Mans reconciliation to God. By Henry Denne an unworthy servant of the Church, ...</title>
                  <author>Denne, Henry, 1606 or 7-1660?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>93 [i.e. 77], [1]; 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the benefit of the city of Rochester,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1645?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Not an STC book.</note>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>In 2 parts; part 2, "Reconciliation of man to God" begins new pagination.</note>
                  <note>There are at least 2 editions : one with imprint and pagination as above, the other with "Citie" in imprint and 78 p.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination; pagination deduced from signature collation.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19323:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19323:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GRACE, MERCY, <hi>AND</hi> PEACE, CONTEINING
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Gods Reconciliation to Man,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Mans Reconciliation to God.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Denne</hi> An unworthy ſervant of the Church,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Not by Arms nor by power but by my ſpirit ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zach:</hi> 4.5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Benefit of the City of <hi>Rochester.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:19323:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19323:2"/>
            <head>A Prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>
               </hi> Lord God, Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who hast given commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto thy Apostles and Ministers <hi>to preach the Goſpell to every Creature;</hi> Bel old O Lord the oppoſitions; and threatnings, which the enemyes of thy Grace have breathed forth against thy truth, and thy ſeruants for thy truths ſake. How they gnaw their toungs for paine, and blaſpheme the God of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting them of their deeds. Behold the troopes that are aſſembled together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Lord, and against his anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſonne Ieſus Christ; for to to doe <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thy hand and thy counſell hath determined before to be done.</hi> Now
<pb facs="tcp:19323:3"/>let the Lord grant unto his ſeruants, that with all boldneſſe they may ſpeake thy word, being nothing terrified by the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie: That the light of the Grace of God, may ſhine in the hearts of his people, that the man of ſin and ſonne of perdition may be destroyed by the brightneſſe of thy comming Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19323:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 10.36.</bibl>
                  <p>Preaching Peace by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto his Apoſtles <hi>Luke</hi> 10 <hi>into whatſoever Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ye come ſay vnto them the Kingdome of God is come nigh unto you</hi> verſe. 9. <hi>And into whatſoever houſe ye enter firſt ſay peace be unto this houſe, And if the ſonne of peace be there your peace ſhall reſt upon it: if not, it ſhall turne to you againe</hi> verſe 5.6. I am this day by the providence of the Almighty, comea <hi>ſtranger</hi> to your City, And now what fitter ſubiect, can I thinke of for a
<pb facs="tcp:19323:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19323:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19323:5"/>
               <hi>ſtranger</hi> to ſpeake unto <hi>ſtrangers</hi> than the glad tidings of Peace by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelius</hi> the centurion, with his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men, and neere Friends, are the <hi>Auditors Peter</hi> is the <hi>preacher.</hi> And this text a part of that <hi>ſermon</hi> at the preaching whereof the <hi>Holy Ghoſt fell on all them which heard the word.</hi> verſe. 44. O that the Lord would vouchſafe that the like effect may this day follow the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>of the word of this life.</hi> That as many as heare me this day; may goe away, <hi>filled with the fullneſse of God.</hi> Peter doth ſeem to ſay in effect, thus much, you are heere met together, to attend unto the word of ſalvation, delivered from my mouth, I can preachto you no other goſpel, then that which was before by the Prophets declared unto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell, in due time to be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (that is to ſay) <hi>Peace by Ieſus Chriſt he is the Lord of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Propoſition from theſe words, is that, the Goſpell, is a Doctrine of Peace, by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine propounded, needeth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19323:5"/>not ſoe much proofe, as explication namely, to ſhew unto you, what manner of Peace this is which is holden forth unto you, by the tender of the glorious Goſpell. I hope you doe not expect, that I ſhould this day declare unto you, any outward, temporall, or worldly Peace; in the middeſt of theſe diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, I would I might, and be yet a true Prophet. The Peace which is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of the Goſpell is like the Kingdom of Chriſt, [being indeed a part of it] <hi>not of this world:</hi> Iohn 18.46. The Peace which came by Ieſus Chriſt, is not an earthly Peace, our bleſſed Saviour will not, that you ſhould entertaine, or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſuch a thought, as this: <hi>Thinke not that I am come to ſend Peace on earth, I came not to ſend Peace, but the ſword; for I am come to ſet the daughter in law againſt her mother in law, and a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be they of his owne houſhould:</hi> Math. 10.34. If any one then ſhall preach unto you, that if you will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Goſpell, you ſhall have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Peace, and proſperity: Is not this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19323:6"/>the preſuptious man ſpeaking His owne words: Is not this the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet propheſying in his own name, whom the Lord hath not ſent? If any chriſtian ſhall embrace the Goſpell, in hope to attain outward felicity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, let me tell him, his thoughts wander from the truth, and he erreth, not knowing the Scriptures, <hi>for if any man will come after me, let him deny himſelf, &amp; take up his croſſe, and follow me.</hi> Mat. 16.24. <hi>And all that will live godly in Chriſt Ieſus muſt ſuffer perſecution.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.12. Heare we alſo what <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.24.25. verſes. <hi>In ſtripes above meaſure, in priſons more frequent, in deaths oft, of the Iews five times received I fourty ſtripes ſave one,</hi> (that is in all 195. ſtripes) <hi>thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I ſtoned, thrice I ſuffered ſhipwrack, a night and a day have I been in the deep, in iorneying often, in perils of waters, in perils of robbers, in perils by mine owne country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in perils by the heathen, in perils in the city, in perils in the wilderneſſe, in perils in the ſea, in perils amongſt falſe brethren,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19323:6"/>In wearines and painfullneſſe, in watchings often In hunger and thirst, In fastings often, In cold and nakedneſſe,</hi> what a catalogue of evils, what an inventory of afflictions have we here? And yet all this and more is the portion of a labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Apoſtle. And if we will ſeek for a true and ſincere Miniſter of the Goſpel, we ſhall, aſſoon find him in poverty and nakedneſſe, as jetting up and down the ſtreets with atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants at his heels, we ſhall aſſoon find him in the univerſitie of <hi>Newgate,</hi> or ſome other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as in great mens houſes, we ſhall aſſoon him in a cloud of reproach, as in a fat benefice or Cathedrall dignity, we ſhall aſſoon finde him at the Bar accuſed, of hereſie, condemned for blaſphemy as in the Courts of Kings, or Princes: for to the inſtruction and conſolation of the people of God be it ſpoken, <hi>they ſhall put you art of their Synagouges, yea the time cometh, that whoſoever killeth you, will think that he doth God ſervice</hi> John 16. Seing then that it is clear, that it is no worldy peace, it remaineth yet to ſhew you what peace this is which the Goſpel preacheth. It is not an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall</hi> peace, but it is <hi>internall.</hi> yea <hi>eternall;</hi> It is a <hi>laſting,</hi> yea an <hi>everlaſting</hi> peace, A peace which no tounge is ſufficient to expreſſe, nor heart to conceive it is even <hi>the love of Christ that paſſeth knowledge</hi> Eph. 3.19. <hi>It is even the peace of God which paſſeth al.</hi> yea angelicall <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> If ſome great and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> angell ſhould undertake to declare this peace to you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19323:7"/>am conſident he would confeſſe his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities too weak, how much more I that am but duſt and aſhes? Surely when I ſhall have told you all that I am able I ſhall not tell you one hundredth part, &amp; when you ſhall underſtand and believe all that you are able, you ſhall not attain unto the leaſt part of that glory which ſhall hereafter be revealed; though I am not able to ſpeak what you deſire, or the thing it ſelf <hi>deſerveth,</hi> yet I will ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout to ſpeak what I am able: And <hi>I</hi> ſhall commend unto you a twofold Peace, the firſt <hi>Deſcending,</hi> The ſecond <hi>aſcending.</hi> The firſt is the tidings of the <hi>love and reconciliation</hi> of the everliving God unto the ſonnes of men.</p>
            <p>The ſecond declares the <hi>reconciliation</hi> of the ſonnes of men to the everliving and everloving God.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak plain, firſt I will ſhew, how <hi>God comes to be reconciled unto men.</hi> Beare with the term <hi>reconciled</hi> although improperly ſpoken of him that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver an euemy. Secondly, I will ſhew you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19323:7"/>
               <hi>how we come to be reconciled unto God.</hi> For the firſt <hi>How doth God come to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conceive now the drooping conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that ſits in darkneſſe under the cloudy apprelhenſion of an angry Iudge, under the fearfull expectation of a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble account, to be given unto the conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, wil be very attentive to heare that which his heart ſo thirſteth after <hi>How God may be reconciled.</hi> Oh what ſhal I doe, ſaith the ſoule, to obtain the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God? What ſhall I doe to turn away his wrathfull diſpleaſure from me wherewith ſhall I come before him? or how ſhall I appeaſe him? Attend there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and I ſhall declare that which thou wilt hardly believe, when it is told un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: for <hi>Lord who hath believed out report, and to whom is the arm of the Lord revealed,</hi> Iſa. 53.1. And yet that which I ſhall declare (if thou canſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, will <hi>fill thy mouth with laughter and thy longue with ſinging,</hi> Pſal. 126.2 Take this propoſition, <hi>God is freely, and fully reconciled to the elect, and loveth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19323:8"/>them in Ieſus Chriſt without any previous diſpoſitions, without any qualifications, without any performances of conditions on their parts, unleſſe to be polluted and finful be a previous condition or qualification.</hi> This is a <hi>bold propoſition</hi> will the phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee ſay, this is too good newes, to be true will the diſtreſſed ſoul ſay. But I ſay the Lord break your ſtony harts, &amp; give you an heart of fleſh, that you may ſubmit to his righteouſnes. And I make no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but the glorious grace of the father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhal abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be manifeſted, The method I intend is 1 <hi>To prove the truth of this propoſition</hi> 2 <hi>To anſwer ſix obiections.</hi> 3 <hi>To make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi> 1 <hi>For the proof,</hi> When <hi>Eve</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> (in whoſe loins we all ſinned had eaten the forbidden fruit, and were now become guilty of condemnation. They hear the voice of God walking in the garden (which voice was this) <hi>thou haſte at en, and thou ſhalt dy</hi>) they hide thmſelves from the preſence of God, amongſt the trees of the garden; when man had ſinn'd &amp; was in a deſpairing condition, having not ſo much wit as to think of a <hi>ſaviour</hi> much
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19323:8"/>leſſe the boldnes to <hi>ask</hi> one at the hands of an offended God.</p>
            <p>Now in this caſe behold the exceed-Love of God towards man, in giving and manifeſting the promiſed ſeed, aſwell to the terrour of Satan; as to the conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankind. And <hi>I will put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy ſeed, and her ſeed, and it ſhall bruiſe his head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heel.</hi> Gen. 3.15 (See if I may compare the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, with the creature) how the Lords bowells <hi>doe yern upon man.</hi> And he cannot refraine himſelf, but that (leaſt man ſhould have been ſwallowed up with ſorrow) the <hi>bleſsing of the promiſed ſeed,</hi> ſhall be firſt declared, before the Lord pronounce, the <hi>leaſt curſe againſt man.</hi> Father <hi>Abraham</hi> receiveth the promiſe in the uncircumciſion of his fleſh. And unto <hi>Adam</hi> is the promiſe revealed, in the uncircumciſion of his heart; but leſt you ſhould think that ſome <hi>qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Adam,</hi> did forerun the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the promiſe, I will referre you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that place of Scripture which (I am
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19323:9"/>reſolved) ſhall never ſlip out of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance (and I hope the like of you) 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. <hi>VVho hath ſaved us, and called us with an holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and grace which was given us in Chriſt Ieſus, before the world began.</hi> What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there, that is not comprehended in this word grace? here you ſee that grace was given before the world began. Now what conditions or qualifictions were there in us before the world began? We may ſafely therefore ſay that <hi>the grace of our God was before all conditions,</hi> &amp;c unto this we will adde in the next place one text, that like a diamond caſteth his luſtre in the dark, and miniſtreth a great meaſure of the ſpirit <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.4.5. <hi>God who is rich in mercie for his great love wherewith the loved us, even when we were dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes hath quickened us together with Chriſt (by grace ye are ſaved.]</hi> What if I ſhall now prove ſo bold, as to make ſuch a ſtop at ſinnes, as ſhall ſhew that that part of the ſentence is referred to that which went
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19323:9"/>before, ſo that we may ſay in plain terms that <hi>God loved us with his great Love, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when we were dead in treſpaſses and ſins.</hi> If I ſhall read it thus, the text will bear it either in the originall, or in other tranſlations. But if any froward perſon ſhall ſay that I doe iniurie in reading it thus and that this clauſe [<hi>dead in treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes &amp; ſins</hi> ought rather to be referred to <hi>quickened,</hi> which followes after then to the verb loved, which goeth before Let this man know that the ſence will be one and the ſame: for when God <hi>quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened</hi> us, then he <hi>loved us, with his great love,</hi> His love being the cauſe of quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening: the effect of his Love, But thou ſayſt <hi>we were quickened when we were, dead in treſpaſses and ſins.</hi> Therefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, we were <hi>loved with his graet love when we were dead</hi> in treſpaſſes and ſins For further confirmation I muſt intreat you to conſider what is written by the Apoſtle Rom. 9.11.12.13 verſes. <hi>For the children being not yet born neither ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done good or evill, that the purpoſe of God according to election might ſtand not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19323:10"/>of works, but of him that calleth, It was ſaid unto her, the elder ſhall ſerve the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as it is written Iacob have I loved, but Eſau, have I hated.</hi> Now you ſee Gods love ſet upon <hi>Iacob,</hi> where were <hi>Iacobs</hi> qualifications? he had neither done good nor evill. Therefore it is plain that God loved him before any qualification. But ſome may confeſſe that the Lord loved him indeed, <hi>before he had done good or evil</hi> And yet may perchance ask a queſtion upon a ſuppoſition, ſaying, ſuppoſe that after <hi>Iacob</hi> was born, he ſhould have led a wicked and perverſe life, ſuppoſe that for ſome yeares, he ſhould have been a notorious, and prophane perſon, <hi>would</hi> or <hi>could</hi> the Lord have continued his love to ſuch a perſon as this? I anſwer boldly yea; for Gods love and mercy, are mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of eternity, <hi>the mercy of the Lord is from everlasting to everlaſting, upon them that feare him Pſal.</hi> 103, 17, <hi>not only to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting,</hi> as eternall in reſpect of time to come, but alſo <hi>from everlasting,</hi> age et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in reſpect of that which is paſt, Gods mercies are not onely <hi>without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19323:10"/>but alſo <hi>without ending,</hi> as it is ſo often repeated even 26 times, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. <hi>his mercy endureth for ever.</hi> This is it that is written by the prophet, <hi>I the Lord, I change not, Therefore yee ſonnes of</hi> Iacob <hi>are not conſumed.</hi> Mal. 3.6. Would you know the true reaſon, why the ſons of <hi>Iacob</hi> are nor conſumed, it is this, <hi>I change not:</hi> ſhould the <hi>Lord change</hi> as often as <hi>we change:</hi> ſhould his love <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and decreaſe</hi> towards us, as often as our love to him, and obedience to his Maieſty, <hi>ebbeth and floweth,</hi> the Lord ſhould be more variable then the wind, more changeable then the Moon, that the Lords love altereth not, although it hath beene ſufficiently proved by that which hath been ſpoken, yet <hi>to the praiſe of the glory of his grace,</hi> I will proceed to ſhew you, by more reſtimonies that the Lord loveth all his elect, with his great love, even then, when as they lie weltring in their ſinnes, &amp; tranſgreſſions. Vnto this the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> bears witneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. verſe. 6. <hi>When we were yet
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19323:11"/>without ſtrength, in due time Chriſt died for the ungodly.</hi> For whó Chriſt <hi>died,</hi> them the Father &amp; the Son <hi>loved;</hi> but Chriſt <hi>died</hi> for the <hi>ungodly,</hi> that were without ſtrength, Therefore ſuch were undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly <hi>beloved of God.</hi> Leſt wee ſhould think the firſt of theſe propoſitions to be weake, it is confirmed, verſe 8. <hi>God commendeth his love to us, in that while we were yet ſinners Chriſt dyed for us.</hi> And very worthy of obſervation is that which is ſpoken verſe 10; <hi>When we were enemies we were reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne.</hi> Here we have more proved than I have yet undertaken; for my task is to prove, <hi>that God was recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to us whilſt we were enemyes.</hi> This text ſaith not onely ſo, <hi>but that we were recontiled to God when we were enemies:</hi> But of this more ſhall be ſpoken here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, only for the preſent we diſire to have it granted, that when we were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to <hi>God,</hi> he was without all doubt reconciled <hi>to us;</hi> for our reconciliation <hi>to him,</hi> is not the cauſe of his reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19323:11"/>
               <hi>to us,</hi> but contrary his reconciliation <hi>to us,</hi> is the cauſe of our reconciliation <hi>to him,</hi> Now let us ſee the argument once againe, <hi>For whom Christ died: thoſe he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But Christ died for vngodly, for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for enemies,</hi> Therefore <hi>hee loved ememies, ſinners, ungodly.</hi> And with ſuch a love, as is not onely <hi>verball,</hi> but <hi>reall,</hi> not in word but in deed &amp; in truth, as doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready appeare by his death, and will; yet more plainly appeare thoſe acts of love, communicated unto us, even when wee were in the ſtate of <hi>vngodlineſse,</hi> in the worſt eſtate and condition. Let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that place ſo full of the glory of God, which is writen, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.2.3. verſes, unto the 15. verſe. <hi>Thou waſt cast out in the open field to the loathing of thy Perſon, in the day that thou waſt born. And when I paſſed by thee, and ſaw thee polluted in thine own blood, I ſaid unto thee in thy blood; yea, I ſaid unto thee in thy blood, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive.</hi> Why doth the Lord uſe this <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemination, In thy blood, In thy blood?</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it not becauſe he knoweth how hardly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19323:12"/>we are drawne to beleeve the <hi>glory of his grace?</hi> and how ready we are to rob him of the honour of his infinite mercy? The Lord doth as it were ſay: I know you will wonder at this, that I ſhould ſay, <hi>Live,</hi> before you were <hi>waſhed, ſalted, or ſwadled,</hi> while you were in your <hi>blood,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I remember the act of my grace which paſſed upon you even in <hi>blood.</hi> I he Lord loved us not becauſe <hi>we were waſhed and cleanſed,</hi> but therefore he <hi>waſhed and cleanſed us,</hi> becauſe he <hi>loved us.</hi> See the freenes of Gods love, <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his onely begotten ſonne that whoſoever believeth on him ſhall not periſh but have everlaſting life.</hi> Ioh. 3.16. This place is wel known unto you, it may be here lies hid ſomething, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you never diſcovered, namely that <hi>Chriſt given is the effect of Gods love, not the cauſe.</hi> And that the <hi>love of God</hi> goes before the <hi>gift of his ſon</hi> as the <hi>cauſe</hi> goeth before the <hi>effect.</hi> He therefore gave his ſonne, becauſe he <hi>loved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this ſeem ſtrange, that <hi>Gods love</hi> ſhould be more ancient, in order of cauſes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19323:12"/>then the <hi>gift of his ſonne,</hi> Becauſe that in him God doth communicate all things unto us, I anſwer, that <hi>Chriſt is God manifeſted to him in the fleſh.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 3.16. And that all the bleſſings of that love, wherewith the Lord loved us eternally, are manifeſted onely in Chriſt Ieſus. And in him they are fully manifeſted to have been for ever in the boſome of the Father: So that for us to ſay or think, that <hi>Chriſt purchaſed the love of the Father for us,</hi> is that which I am confident the redeemer of the world will not chalenge unto himſelf. But ſay (as in another caſe) <hi>it is not mine to give,</hi> but it was given to them, to whom it is given before the foundation of the world was laid, This is all that I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpeak, unleſſe it ſhould be lawfull for me, in ſo reverend a myſtery, to uſe a diſtinction, and to conſider in the love of God the <hi>original</hi> of his love, and the <hi>continuation</hi> thereof, and to ſay that the <hi>original</hi> of his love was before the gift of his ſonne, as the cauſe before the effect But that the <hi>continuation</hi> of love, is to be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19323:13"/>referred unto the propriation of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, as the effect of that ſacrifice which he offered, To ſpeak plain, <hi>Gods love</hi> was before the gift of his ſon, as the cauſe before the effect. But the <hi>continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of that love, that he ſhould loveus for ever, requires a foregoing <hi>propitiation &amp; ſatisfaction.</hi> But when we ſhal ſay thus, we fall into a depth unſearchable, when we ſhall ask why the continuation of his love ſhould rather require a foregoing <hi>propitiation,</hi> then the <hi>originall</hi> ſetting of his love upon us. I confeſſe I cannot tell what to ſay, for to cleare this; but trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpeak of this glerious myſtery, And deſire to refer my ſelf to the iudgement of the ſpirituall, who are able to iudge all things, and to be inſtructed by them, whether it be not ſafer to reſt, in that which was ſaid before, then with ſubtilty of diſtinctions, to wade into the depth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable. We ſee the great love of God to us <hi>in our bloud,</hi> how that he ſo loved us, that he <hi>gave us his ſonne,</hi> I will now be bold to ſtep a ſtep higher, if higher may
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19323:13"/>be, and to ſhew you that God did not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love us in our bloud, with his great love; But that his love to us in our broud <hi>was as great as ever afterwards.</hi> He loved us, I ſay, <hi>with as great love when we were in bloud and polltion as he did afterward when we were cleanſed.</hi> I know the Phariſee will ſtamp at this, and ſay, Doth God love us aſwell <hi>before</hi> converſion as <hi>after</hi> converſion? Did God love <hi>Paul,</hi> with as great a love when that he perſecuted the Church, as when he preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell? I will anſwer boldly, yea he did, And that I ſhall by the aſſiſtance of God prove unto you, againſt men, or de ills who ſhall oppoſe it. That God loved us being <hi>dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes,</hi> you have heard proved: now give mee leave to propound a queſtion, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this great love wherewith God loved ſinners, be not his <hi>infinite love</hi> like himſelf? nay, whether is it any other thing then him ſelf? <hi>God is love.</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.16. If this be granted that Gods love is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite to ſinners, that it is like himſelf,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19323:14"/>yea, that it is himſelfe: for love in God is not a quality: Then it will be plaine, that his love is not capable of <hi>increaſe or decreaſe,</hi> but is alwayes <hi>one and the ſame.</hi> The difference is in us, whoſe apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions doe often <hi>increaſe</hi> and <hi>decreaſe.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, is not the <hi>love of God</hi> to be weighed by the pledges of his <hi>love?</hi> But we ſhall find the greateſt pledges of his love to be given unto ſinners even in the ſtate of ungodlineſſe. What greater pledge than the gift of his Sonne? <hi>In this God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth his love, &amp;c.</hi> as before. Rom. 5.8. All the mercies of God are commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of his love, but none like this: All other gifts are not comparable to the gift of his Sonne. <hi>He thht ſpared not his owne Sonne, but delivered him up for us all, how ſhall he not with him alſo freely give us all things?</hi> Rom. 8.32. If all things were laid in one ballance, and the Sonne of God in the other, no man doubteth, but that the Sonne of God would bee iufinitely beyond all things. <hi>Greater love than this hath no man, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19323:14"/>a man lay down his life for his friend,</hi> John 15.13. But <hi>greater love</hi> hath God, in that he laid down his life for his <hi>enemies. In this was manifeſted the love of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, becauſe that God ſent his onely begotten Son into the world, that wee might live through him. Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that God loved us, and ſent his Sonne to be the propitiation for our ſinnes,</hi> 1 Iohn 4.9.10. Now that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>In this was manife sted the love of God.</hi> And, <hi>Herein is love,</hi> he doth it to this end, that hee might ſhew unto us, that Chriſt was the greateſt manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of Gods love: <hi>Hereby perceive we the love of God, That he hath laid down his life for us,</hi> 1 Iohn 3.16. Theſe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are all comparative, ſhewing us that Gods <hi>loue</hi> was manifeſt in nothing more, or rather nothing ſo much, as in the <hi>death of his Son. Abrahams</hi> love to God appeared in many things; but above all, in that he denied not his Sonne. For <hi>now I know thai thou feareſt God, ſeeing thou haſt not with-held thy ſonne, thine onely
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19323:15"/>ſonne from me, Gen,</hi> 22.12. May not we iuſtly ſay with admiration unto God, <hi>Now we know that thou loveſt us, becauſe thou hast not with-held thy Sonne, thine onely Sonne,</hi> Thus you ſee God doth not onely <hi>love</hi> us before converſion, but he loveth us with his <hi>great love,</hi> yea <hi>his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt love</hi> that ever was communicated to the creature: for greater love did God never manifeſt to the creature, than that hee ſhould give his Sonne. This may more fully appeare by ſeverall effects of the love of God, communicated unto men, by God, in and through his Sonne; before converſion, faith, &amp;c. or any thing in us preconſidered. <hi>He hath choſen us in him before the foundation of the world. Eph.</hi> 1.4. Again, <hi>Hee hath predeſtinated us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the adoption of ſonnes, by Ieſus Christ to himſelfe, according to the good pleaſure of his will, to the praiſe of the glory of his grace, wherein he hath made us accepted in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, in whom we have redemption through his bloud, even the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, according to the riches of his grace,</hi> verſes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19323:15"/>5.6.7. <hi>In whom alſo we have obtained an inheritance, being predeſtinated according to the purpoſe of him, who worketh all things after the counſell of his own will,</hi> verſe 11. How many acts of God have wee here comunicated by his grace unto the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, before repentance, faith, or conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or calling. We will adde to theſe one act of grace more communicated to the creature in the ſtate of ungodlineſſe. <hi>God juſtifieth the ungodly,</hi> Rom. 4.5. yea take wee ſanctificaiion in the common acception, may we not ſay God ſanctiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ungodly. For men are not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied becauſe they are godly, but godly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſanctified. Yea one thing more, even <hi>Calling</hi> it ſelf, <hi>effectual Calling</hi> I meane, goes before converſion, as the cauſe before the effect: for calling is not an effect of converſion, but converſion is an effect of calling. It is neceſſary that God call before wee can heare; yea that God open the heart before wee can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. If I did think that theſe things nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded proofe, I would ſpend time about it.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19323:16"/>You ſee now, Predeſtination, Chooſing, Redemption, Iuſtification, Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Calling, opening of the Heart, all of them gracious acts of God, communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto the creature before the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the creature to God. Let us heare the Lord ſpeaking of his own work upon the creature, Eſay 57.18. <hi>Hee went on frowardly in the way of his heart; I have ſeen his wayes and will heale him, I will lead him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and restore comforts to him, and to his mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> Whom wilt thou heale? O Lord whom wilt thou reſtore? Even him whoſe wayes I have ſeen. What are thoſe wayes? Even frowardneſſe and perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Hee went in frowardly in the way of his heart.</hi> See againe, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 43.25. <hi>I, even I am hee that blotteth out thy tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for mine owne ſake, and will not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy ſinnes.</hi> Whoſe ſins will the Lord blot our? Looke wee back unto the 22. verſe, <hi>Thou haſt not called upon mee, O Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coh, thou hast been weary of mee, O Iſrael, Thou haſt made me to ſerve with thy ſinnes, Thou hast wearied me with thine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> verſe 24. See, Thou haſt been wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19323:16"/>of me, yea thou haſt wearied me. This is <hi>Iacohs</hi> qualiſication. This is <hi>Iſraels</hi> preparation. Then followes, <hi>I, even I, am he that blotteth out thy tranſgreſſions.</hi> As if the Lord would ſay unto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as he ſpeaketh by the prophet <hi>Ezek.</hi> Chap. 36.22. <hi>Say unto the houſe of Iſrael, Thus ſaith the Lord God, I doe not this for your ſake, O houſe of Iſraell, but for my holy names ſake, which ye have profaned among the Heathen, whither ye went,</hi> or as when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was neer the confines of <hi>Canaan</hi> The Lord ſpeaketh thus unto them by <hi>Moſes, underſtand therefore, that the Lord thy God giveth thee not this good land to poſsoſſe it for thy righteouſneſſe, for thou art a ſtiffnecked people.</hi> Deut. 9.6. As if the Lod ſhould ſay, I will blot out your tranſgreſſions. But I would have you know the riches of my grace. It is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing in you that moveth me unto it. For there is nothing in you but rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but I doe it for my glory ſake. As the Prophet ſpeaketh in the name of the Lord, Eſay 48.8.9. <hi>I knew that thou wouldeſt deale very treachercuſly, and was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19323:17"/>called a tranſgreſſour from the womb: for my names ſake will I deferre mine anger, and for my praiſe will I refraine for thee, that I cut thee not off.</hi> This is all the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification we bring unto God, to win his love and mercie: We are rebellious, we are prophane, we are a ſtiffe necked peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And if the Lord ſhould not love us, untill hee find lovely conditions in us, ſurely he muſt hate us for ever: If God ſhould not be reconciled unto us, untill we be reconciled unto him: he muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue our enemy for ever. Wherefore conſidering what hath been ſaid, we will be bold to conclude to the praiſe of the glory of his grace, that <hi>his love and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to us, is before all qualifications in us: that his love and mercy to us, is the cauſe of all qualifications in us. That his love towards us is as great before faith and converſion as after.</hi> There is no difference in him. But ſome will ſay, peradventure we grant that God thus loveth us, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prov'd; but it may be it was becauſe hee foreſaw we would be good, repent, beleeve, &amp;c. Farre bee it from us to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19323:17"/>ſuch thoughts. He that well pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth what hath beene ſaid, ſhall well perceive, that God doth not therefore love us, becauſe hee foreſaw we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and beleeve, but therefore cauſeth us to repent, and beleeve in his time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loveth us.</p>
            <p>But to make this alſo more cleare, the holy Ghoſt declares, <hi>That the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God towards man, appeared not by works of righteouſneſse which we have done, but according to his mercy he ſaved us,</hi> Tit. 3.4 5. The paterne according to which God ſetteth his love upon man, was not any thing ſave his rich mercy, whereby it is plain, <hi>Not that wee loved him, but that he loved us,</hi> 1 Iohn 4.10. <hi>Yee have not choſen mee, but I have choſen you,</hi> Iohn 15.16. As our Father <hi>Abraham</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the righteouſneſſe of faith being yet uncircumciſed, and then received the ſigne of circumciſion, a ſeale of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of faith which hee had yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uncircumciſed: So as <hi>Abraham</hi> was firſt righteous, and then circumciſed; not firſt circumciſed, and then righteous:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19323:18"/>So the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> are firſt <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved</hi> and then <hi>converted,</hi> not firſt <hi>convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and then <hi>beloved,</hi> And as God did not account <hi>Abraham</hi> righteous becauſe he foreſaw he would be circumciſed, But therefore he gave him the ſigne of Circumciſion becauſe he had made him righteous. So it is with the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> God doth not therefore love them, becauſe he foreſeeth they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and believe, but therefore he cauſeth them in his time to repent and believe the Goſpel, becauſe he loved them. Thus have I done with the firſt thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in the handling of this propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: The ſecond followes, namely the anſwer unto the ſeverall obiections. The firſt and greateſt is this, if God love the elect while they are yet <hi>dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes,</hi> tand ſo love them with his great love, and with as great a love before couverſion as after, as is before proved. then how is it ſaid. Pſalm 5.5. <hi>Thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt all the workers of iniquity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hither we may reſerre many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19323:18"/>of Scripture of like nature. <hi>If God hate all the workers of iniquity,</hi> how can he be ſaid <hi>to love the ungodly?</hi> Thus you ſee in one ſhort ſentence, ſeemeth to be quite overthrown all that I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſpoken. To wind out of this labarinth, which ſome having aſſayed, have further intangled themſelves (with invocation unto <hi>God</hi> for the wiſedome of his <hi>holy Spirit</hi> to guid us into the truth) I will firſt ſhew you what ſome have ſaid to clear this; and then I ſhall deliver unto you mine own iudgement: And yet, I hope, not mine owne, but the iudgement of the Spirit of God, and of moſt of the Saints of God. Firſt then, I find a great Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Doctor (moving the obiection, and labouring to give ſolution) to give us this diſtinction; That God hates the workes, but nor the perſons of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. I will not ſtand to queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there may be ſuch a diſtinction ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or no, but will take it for grant; and yet I doe believe ſinne to be of that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19323:19"/>hideous nature, and the iuſtice of God ſo perfect, that he cannot but hate the perſon, unto whom hee imputeth, and upon whom he chargeth ſinne, if ſo be the perſon charged cannot give full, perfect, and preſent ſatisfaction. And yet will I not ſay, that the Sonne of God. upon whom all our iniquities, <hi>great and ſmall, were charged,</hi> was at any time, <hi>Filius odii,</hi> a ſonne of hatred (for the father was eternally <hi>well pleaſed with him</hi>) the reaſon is, that our ſinnes were no ſooner charged upon him, but that hee had given full and perfect ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>being the Lamh ſlain from the foundation of the world, Rev.</hi> 13.8. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſoreſaid diſtinction of perſon and workes, ſhould be granted, without further queſtion, yet give me leave to pronounce it nothing pertinent to the ſolution of the Obiection in hand: For the Text ſaith not onely <hi>he hateth the works, but the workers,</hi> (that is, the perſons working) <hi>iniquite.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother anſwer is brought to untie this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19323:19"/>knot, by a jiugling diſtinction of a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold love in God, namely, <hi>Amor bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volentiae,</hi> and, <hi>amor complacentiae,</hi> that the ſimple may underſtand, there is in God, ſay they, a <hi>love of well willing,</hi> and a <hi>love of liking.</hi> Now God (ſay they) loves his elect before their converſion, with the love of <hi>well-willing,</hi> but not with the <hi>love of liking.</hi> Like unto which we heare of a diſtinction not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Of the love of <hi>Election,</hi> and the love of <hi>Iustification.</hi> God (ſay they) loves his elect with the love of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but not with the love of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Firſt of all, I deſire you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether there be not more time then reaſon in theſe diſtinctions; the love of <hi>Election,</hi> and the love of <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> being not diverfities of love, or divers degrees of love, but divers <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestations</hi> of one and the ſame infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite love. As when a Father hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed an inheritance to his Sonne, here is no new love from the Father to the Sonne, but a new manifeſtation of that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19323:20"/>love, wherewith the father loved the ſonne before. Secondly, how can it be that God ſhould not like the perſon whom he loves? There is indeed this difference betwen <hi>Humane</hi> love and <hi>Divine;</hi> Men commonly <hi>love</hi> becauſe they <hi>like:</hi> but God <hi>likes</hi> becauſe hee <hi>loves.</hi> Man cannot but <hi>love</hi> where hee <hi>likes.</hi> And I beleeve (ſpeaking of the perſon) God cannot but <hi>like</hi> where hee <hi>loves.</hi> To make ſuch differences of love in God, will I feare open a gap to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny foule abſurdities. But ſuppoſe that theſe things could be ſo, it will appeare that God loves the perſons of his elect, not only with a love of <hi>Benevolence,</hi> but a ſo with a love of <hi>Complacence</hi> and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: For this ia the voyc of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from heaven, <hi>This my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> Matth. 3.17. Here is a revelation of the love of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, <hi>I am well pleaſed:</hi> The Father is well pleaſed in his Son. With whom? Surely with thoſe unto whom hee had given his Sonne, that is, all his elect. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19323:20"/>this anſwer, if it were beyond all exceptions, yet it is very impertinent to the obiection: For the Text doth not onely ſay, that God <hi>loveth</hi> them not with ſuch or ſuch a love, but in plaine terms it ſaith, that <hi>the Lord hateth them that work iniquity.</hi> Now what ſhall we ſay, that <hi>God</hi> loves a perſon with <hi>infinit a love,</hi> beyond expreſſion, or conceit, and yet at the ſame time, hateth the ſame perſon with that <hi>perfect hatred</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee hateth all the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie. Let us take heed that we draw not a vaile before the face of God, and delude our ſelves and others with ſuch frothy and impertinent diſtinctions. But I have by this time bred a kinde of wonder in you; what I ſhall ſpeak, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which other men have ſaid thus far, liketh me not. I anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that this clauſe, <hi>God hateth all the workers of iniquity,</hi> and <hi>God loveth the ungodly,</hi> are both in Scripture, and therefore both true; yet in a different ſenſe. The firſt, <hi>The Lord hateth all the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19323:21"/>workers of iniquity,</hi> is the voyce of the <hi>Law:</hi> the other, the Lord loves <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> is the voyce of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> Now the Law, and the Goſpel ſpeak divers things; the one being the manifeſtation of Gods iuſtice, tells us what we are by nature: the other, being the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods mercie, tells us what wee are by grace in Ieſus Chriſt. The <hi>Law</hi> ſaith, that <hi>every ſinner ſhal be accurſed.</hi> The <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners.</hi> The <hi>Law</hi> ſaith, <hi>God will by no meanes cleare the guilty,</hi> Exod. 34.7. The <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſaith, <hi>God ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth the ungodly.</hi> The <hi>Law</hi> declareth wrath without forgiveneſſe: The <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> Mercy, grace and peace in Ieſus Chriſt. Thus farre is the obiection an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; but yet all difficulty and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is not removed: For the <hi>Law,</hi> you will ſay, is an eternall veritie, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it ſaith, is true. I confeſſe it ſo, and one iot or tittle thereof cannot faile. But I ſay, with the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that <hi>whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Law ſaith, it ſaith to them only,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19323:21"/>who are under the Law,</hi> and to none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I ſay again, <hi>that the righteouſneſſe of the Law is fulfilled by Chriſt for us all; yea in all that walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8.4. So that although the elect of <hi>God</hi> are ſinners in the iudgement of the <hi>Law, Senſe, Reaſon,</hi> yea and oftentimes <hi>Conſcience;</hi> yet having their ſinnes tranſlated unto the Sonne of God, (in whom they were elected) they have the righteouſneſſe of the <hi>Law</hi> fulfilled in the Mediatour, and ſo become to be accounted righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in his ſight; that as God on the one ſide delivered the <hi>innocent to death,</hi> as though hee had been a ſinner, being made countable for our ſinnes: So on the other ſide, God <hi>loveth, juſtifieth, cleareth</hi> the guilty and ſinners, as if they had been <hi>holy, righteous,</hi> and <hi>blameleſſe.</hi> The ſumme is this, that as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>no ſinner indeed,</hi> and yet <hi>a ſinner by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation;</hi> ſo they that are <hi>Chriſis,</hi> are no ſinners by <hi>imputation,</hi> and yet <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:19323:22"/>
            <p> Thus much for the firſt Obiection. The ſecond followes.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Objection <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If <hi>God</hi> be reconciled unto us, <hi>before all condtions, &amp;c.</hi> How is it that our Saviour ſaith, Matth. 6.15. <hi>If you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give not men their treſpaſses, neither will your heavenly Father forgive you your treſpaſses.</hi> Vnto which may be ioined that which we have, Matth. 18.35. <hi>So likewiſe ſhall my heavenly doe alſo unto you, if yee from your heart forgive not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very on his brother their treſpaſses.</hi> In which place we ſee, firſt, that <hi>unleſſe we forgive, God will not forgive us:</hi> Nay more, that God will reverſe the act of his mercy, if after hee hath <hi>forgiven</hi> us 10000. talents, wee ſhall not <hi>forgive</hi> 100. pence, wee ſhall bee delivered to the tormentors, until we pay the whole due. For anſwer to this Obiection, we muſt lay down two grounds; the firſt, <hi>That God rever reverſeth the acts of his mercy communicated to his Elect. For the gifts and calling of God are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19323:22"/>without repentance,</hi> Rom. 112.9. <hi>God is not a man that he ſhould lie, neither the ſonne of man that he ſhould repent,</hi> 1 Sam. 23.19. The ſecond ground, that <hi>Gods forgiveneſs of us is a fore-runner of our forgivenes of our brethren.</hi> And we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not truly forgive our brethren, untill wee doe apprehend Gods forgiveneſſe of us. <hi>Shouldeſt not thou have had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on thy fellow-ſervant, even as I had pitie on thee?</hi> Matth. 18.33. And upon this ground the Apoſtle preſſeth the <hi>Epheſians</hi> unto kindneſſe and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of heart, <hi>forgiving one another, even as God for Chriſts ſake hath forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you,</hi> Eph. 4.3.</p>
               <p>But then if this be ſo, what meane the foreſaid places, which ſtrengthen the objection? I anſwer: That <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe</hi> is there to bee taken for the manifeſtation of forgiveneſſe: <hi>Except ye forgive men, neither will your heavenly Father ſo fully declare, and manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe unto your conſciences;</hi> and ſo this place pertaineth properly to our recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19323:23"/>with God, not unto Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with us. That this is not a ſubtile evaſion, but the truth, appeares firſt by a place of Scripture; ſecondly, by the judgement of Interpreters upon a like place: The place of Scripture is found <hi>Luke</hi> 7.47. <hi>Her ſinnes which are many are forgiven her, for ſhee loved much.</hi> What have wee here? that this womans great love was the cauſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or that it went before her ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of remiſſion, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth? Verily no: but it is plaine, that her <hi>remiſsion obtained,</hi> was the <hi>cauſe of her love. Simon,</hi> ſaith our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> A certaine creditor forgave two debtors frankly: whereof the one ought five hundred pence, the other fifty; which of the twain wil love him moſt? <hi>Simon</hi> anſwereth <hi>well, He to whom he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave moſt.</hi> Our <hi>Saviour</hi> maketh the application; Seeſt thou this <hi>woman?</hi> Thou loveſt me a <hi>little,</hi> Thou haſt bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den me to dinner. But when I came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy houſe, <hi>thou gaveſt me no mater for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19323:23"/>my feet;</hi> but ſhee, hath <hi>waſhed my feet with her teares, and wiped them with the haires of her head. My head with oyle thou diddeſt not anoint, but this woman hath anointed my feet with ointment.</hi> Thou ſeeſt, that I have forgiven thee a <hi>few ſinnes,</hi> and thou loveſt mee a <hi>little,</hi> but this woman hath <hi>much</hi> forgiven her: Therefore <hi>ſhe loved much:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we underſtand two things; firſt, that her <hi>love</hi> was not the cauſe of <hi>forgivenes,</hi> but <hi>forgiveneſſe</hi> a cauſe of her <hi>love.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That <hi>forgiveneſſe</hi> in this place includeth the <hi>manifeſtation of forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> many ſinnes are forgiven her, the ſenſe is this, it appeareth unto this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that I have pardoned a <hi>multitude of ſinnes</hi> for her. This is the Scripture.</p>
               <p>The judgement of Interpreters in the Proteſtant Church, upon a like place, is occaſioned by an argument ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and other poplings, againſt the Proteſtants, on this wiſe: If, ſaith he, the Proteſtants have pardon of all their ſinnes, in ſuch
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19323:24"/>wiſe as they ſay they have, why doe they yet pray, <hi>forgive us our treſpaſſes?</hi> if they be already <hi>forgiven?</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants anſwer with one conſent: that they doe beg at the hands of God, <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter certainty,</hi> and <hi>aſſurance</hi> of his grace towards them: the Petition <hi>forgive us our treſpaſſes, may well ſtand with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of pardon.</hi> The condemned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that is upon the ladder, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the pardon of a gracious Prince, heares it read; is aſſured of it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth in it, yet this perſon being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into the preſence of the King, if he ſhould fall downe and ſay, <hi>Pardon mee my Lord the King;</hi> who could lay folly to his charge? So we having received the free pardon of ſinne at his hand al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, yet as oft as wee come into his preſence wee cry to the glory of his grace, <hi>forgive us our treſpaſſes:</hi> for while we beg at the hands of God, that which we have before received, we doe magniſie his grace, that hath freely gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it. Againe, who ſo ſure, and certain
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19323:24"/>of pardon, but that he either needeth a greater aſſurance, or at leaſt that aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to be by Gods mercy continued. Thus much for the ſecond objection. The third followeth. If God love us <hi>in bloud and pollution, as well before conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as after converſion;</hi> then to what purpoſe ſerve our <hi>faith and good workes?</hi> Firſt, I anſwer this objection indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by propounding one queſtion; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou thinkeſt that thy faith and good workes can obtaine, or procure the love and favour of God. If thou ſayeſt no, then why doeſt thou make this objection? If thou ſayeſt yea, then I demand, who ſhall give thee faith and good workes? Shouldſt thou expect them from any other then from the hand of a loving God? Secondly, I anſwer directly, by ſhewing thee the true office of faith: Although faith do not procure Gods love and favour, yet is it to very good purpoſe, and exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing precious: That you may know the love of God, and be ſealed with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19323:25"/>Spirit of promiſe. <hi>In whom after yee beleeved ye were ſealed with the holy ſpirit of promiſe; which is the earneſt of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance unto the redemption of the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed poſſeſsion, unto the praiſe of his glory, Eph.</hi> 1.13, 14. The Originall reades it, <hi>In whom beleeving ye were ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led:</hi> ſo that <hi>beleeving</hi> is <hi>ſealing,</hi> and an earneſt of the inheritance. Secondly, that <hi>beleeving</hi> you who were under darkneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death, and ſaw no light, yet I ſay <hi>beleeving yee might rejoyce with ioy unſpeakable, and full of glory, receiving the end of your faith,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. <hi>The God of hope fill you with all ioy and peace in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee your faith is to very good purpoſe, and yet not to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to obtaine the love and favour of God. Thus much for the office of faith; yet doe I not undertake, to ſet out unto you the whole office of that moſt precious gift, but on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo much as may ſerve to anſwer the preſent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19323:25"/>But ſecondly, to what purpoſe ſerve our good workes? I anſwer, to very good purpoſe alſo: namely, to expreſſe our <hi>thankfulnes</hi> to God, and our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red us from our enemies: <hi>That we being delivered might ſerve him without feare in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before him all the dayes of our life, Luke</hi> 1.74, 75. We doe not ſerve God to obtaine deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance by ſerving of him. But of his free grace obtaining deliverance wee ſerve him. Wee doe not ſerve God to obtaine ſalvation, but obtaining ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion freely by Ieſus Chriſt, we offer up our ſouls and bodies, a living ſacrifice of thankſgiving. I anſwer further, Thy good workes may bee <hi>profitable unto men, Tit.</hi> 3.8. but <hi>not unto God,</hi> who is of abſolute perfection, and needeth not any thing which thou canſt doe. <hi>Can a man be profitable unto God, as he that is wiſe may be profitable unto himſelfe? Is it any pleaſure to the Almighty that thou art righteous? or is it any gaine to him
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19323:26"/>that thou makeſt thy wayes perfect? Iob</hi> 22.2.3. Thus you ſee the office of your faith and workes. Becauſe we ſay that God loves us as well before converſion as after, doe wee therefore make faith and workes void? God forbid. Muſt I needs put out my <hi>fire,</hi> becauſe I will not ſet it on the <hi>top of the houſe?</hi> No, I will keepe it within the <hi>chimney,</hi> which is the proper place. Woe be to that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, where the ſire ſhall overtop the houſes: <hi>fire</hi> is precious in the <hi>chimney,</hi> bur <hi>dangerous</hi> elſewhere. Precious is the gift of <hi>faith,</hi> if kept within his own ſphere; but if we ſhall begin to lift it up, and place it in the throne of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> what rock more dangerous to the ſoul? The <hi>Braſen Serpent</hi> was a great bleſſing ſo long as <hi>Iſrael</hi> looked at it by Gods appointment, to be healed of the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the fiery Serpents. But when once <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall burne incenſe unto it, let it be <hi>Nehuſhtan,</hi> a peece of old can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kred braſſe, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.4. Thus for the third obiection, the fourth follows.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19323:26"/>
               <p> If God love us <hi>with as great a love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore converſion as after,</hi> then what need we take care what we doe? If we repent and beleeve, the Lord will love us ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the better; If we neither repent nor beleeve, the Lord will love us never the worſe. Anſwer. I can hardly vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to give an anſwer to this obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe the wiſe man adviſeth, <hi>Pro.</hi> 26.4. <hi>Anſwer not a Foole according to his folly, leſt thou bee like unto him.</hi> And yet I muſt give an anſwer, becauſe the wiſe man commandeth, <hi>verſe</hi> 5. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer a Foole according to his folly, leſt hee bee wiſe in his owne conceit.</hi> Leſt if I ſhould paſſe by this obiection, thou ſhouldeſt triumph as if thou hadſt got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the victory. I anſwer therfore with the Apoſtle, <hi>Shall we ſin that grace may abound, and ſhall we ſin becauſe wee are not under the Law, but under Grace? God forbid,</hi> Ron 6.15. This obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was moved by cavelling ſpirits even in the Apoſtles time, well nigh 1600 years agoe, and you ſee the anſwer. And
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19323:27"/>now the ſame ſpirit rageth in thee. But I thought what a cuſtomer vvee ſhould have of thee. Thou vvouldeſt make men beleeve, that thou art no <hi>Iuſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> no <hi>Papiſt,</hi> not one that ſeekes to bee iuſtified by thy workes. And yet if thy workes cannot <hi>obtain Gods favour,</hi> if they cannot procure an <hi>increaſe of his love,</hi> thou will preſently caſt off all, and give liberty to thy fleſh. Give me leave to ſpeak plain, <hi>Thou art hee that turneſt the grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt into wantonnes, whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe God is thy belly, whoſe glory is thy ſhame, who mindeſt earthly things,</hi> Philip. 3.19. But bee it known unto thee, that the <hi>grace of God teacheth</hi> (other things, namely) <hi>to deny alungodlines and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I perceive by this objection, that thou accountedſt this a doctrine of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, to declare the free love of God in Ieſus Chriſt: and thou thinkeſt it were better to hide this from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19323:27"/>and to terrifie them with Hell fire, with wrath, and iudgement, and with the fierie flaſhings of Mount Sinai, and to keepe them in bondage. I can hardly refraine from giving thee very evill language, that art thus preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and audacious to contradict the Lord Ieſus, who hath given comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement that the Goſpel of peace ſhould bee preached to all Nations. I will ſpare to ſpeake what I think, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto thy conſideration the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one of our owne Countrimen, whoſe learning was by his adverſaries commended, whoſe conſtancie and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in his martyrdome was admired: it was <hi>Iohn Fryth;</hi> who writeth to this effect: Thou maiſt preach hell and damnation, and the rendring of a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible account to a ſevere Iudge, &amp;c. ſeven yeares together, and yet not make one good Chriſtian man. Hee that would make a good Chriſtian, let the love of God be the firſt ſtone, which he layeth for the foundation. Thus hee
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19323:28"/>ſpeaketh. And indeed what motive to obedience ſo ſtrong as love? Many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cannot quench love, neither can the flouds drowne it, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.7. What greater feare then that which procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from love? If wee have an enemy whom we hate, wee ſheath a ſword it his bowels, or cleave his head with a Polax, and cry him no mercy: but how carefull are we not to do the leaſt iniury to a friend? if we tread on his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, we are ſory at the heart. What greater aggravation of ſinne, then to ſin againſt love? Were not he an ungraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and rebellious ſonne amongſt men, who ſhould reaſon thus: I have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Father, who loveth me excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, deemeth nothing too good for me, who hath given mee aſſurance and poſſeſſion of his whole inheritance, therefore I will ſurely neglect him, I will ſhew my ſelfe undutifull againſt him, I will no more regard his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, or attend unto his precepts, but whatſoever will grieve him, that will I
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19323:28"/>doe. What heart could not afford to caſt a ſtone at the head of ſuch a ſonne of <hi>Belial</hi> as this, to daſh out his brains? For ſhame let the mover of this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection bluſh, and hide his head, let him conſider his folly. The caſe is thine, thou art the man; becauſe God aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in free love, mercy, and kindneſſe, therefore thou wilt abound in wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe. I ceaſe to ſpeak any farther of this to thy greater ſhame. The fifth obiection followes, which is indeed more mannerly than the former.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Object. <hi>5.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If God love us, bee reconciled unto us, before our faith and our converſion, then a man may poſſibly dye without faith, and yet be ſaved.</p>
               <p>I anſwer: This followeth not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath ingaged himſelfe to the contrary: which if he had not dore, much might have beene ſaid. But wee ſee, hee that cannot lye, hath ingaged himſelfe unto his people: <hi>I will put my Law into their hearts, &amp; in their minds
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19323:29"/>will I write them,</hi> Heb. 10.6. <hi>And all ſhall know me from the leaſt to the greateſt</hi> Heb. 8.11. <hi>All thy children ſhall bee taught of God,</hi> Iohn 6.54. Iſaiah 54.13. So that we ſay, <hi>He that beleeveth not ſhall bee damned.</hi> Not becauſe his believing doth alter or change his eſtate before God; but becauſe the God of truth hath promiſed, that hee will not onely give us remiſſion, but that he wil alſo give faith for our conſolation; and ſo faith becommeth a note and mark of life everlaſting, and finall infidelity a ſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of eternall condemnation; that whoſoever, or whatſoever he be in life or converſation, yet <hi>hee that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not ſhall be damned.</hi> Thus much for the fifth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Object. <hi>6.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The ſixth obiection: If God love us as you ſay, why doth he ſuffer us to live in 20.50. or 60. yeares?</p>
               <p>I anſwer: <hi>What art thou that replieſt againſt God? How unſearchable are his judgements, and his wayes paſt finding
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19323:29"/>out?</hi> Rom. 11.33. Againe, let us aske <hi>Paul,</hi> why the Lord ſuffered him (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an elect and choſen veſſell) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute his Saints unto death and bonds, and to cauſe many to blaſpheme; and hee will tell us, that <hi>in him firſt Ieſus Chriſt might ſhew forth all long ſuffering for a patterne to them which ſhould here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after beleeve on him to life everlaſting,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.16. Thirdly, thou mayeſt as well obiect, ſeeing that God is of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite power, why doth he ſuffer ſinne in the world? if thou ſhouldeſt, the Lord will give anſwer, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.9. Thus farre for the obiections, now wee come to the third thing propounded, The applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what hath been ſpoken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Applicat. <hi>1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In the firſt place we will obſerve the difference betweene the true Religion and the falſe, from that which hath been ſpoken. There are many religions in the world. And it fareth with diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Religions, as with diverſities of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19323:30"/>opinions: there is a poſſibility that they may be all falſe, but it is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoſſible that they ſhould be all true. There is but one true Religion, but there are many falſe: the falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions ſeeming to differ exceedingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, in very many things even in the obiect of worſhip, and in the matter, and manner; yet be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo different, there is one common foundation, wherein they doe all agree, and wherein they differ from the true. The true Religion propoundeth unto us a God in chiefe reconciled, pacified, pleaſed, a juſtice already ſatisfied, a propitiation made, ſinnes taken away: and we have not one jote, not one apex in all the new Covenant to be found of reconciling God to us, but of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to God: The new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant manifeſteth unto us a God alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy reconciled to us, and the whole mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of reconciliation propoundeth our reconciliation to God. Now this is the common character of all falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19323:30"/>of what ſort ſoever, Iews, Turks Papiſts, phariſaicall Proteſtants, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, all propound in ſome degree or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, an angry God, a deity not recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, and then preſcribe certain means and ſervices whereby to appeaſe his wrath, and to quench his diſpleaſure, and to obtaine his love and favour. Man doth not oftner ſeeke after ſalvation, but hee naturally ſtumbleth upon this principle, <hi>What ſhall I doe to be ſaved?</hi> The world would bee ſaved by doing. <hi>Martin Luther</hi> ſpeaking of this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, doth more than once compare the falſe religions unto <hi>Sampſons</hi> foxes, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 15.4. their heads looking divers wayes, but they were faſtned together by the tayles. This compariſon wee doe imbrace; yet I had rather compare them to Gentlemens Spaniels, which are faſtned together by the necks, but looſe at the tayles. They differ indeed in ſome circumſtances, but in the main ſubſtance they agree in one. Doe wee not ſee ſome men contending with the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19323:31"/>Papiſt, with wonderfull eagerneſſe? doe we not ſee others tugging, and haling, one one way, the other another, one for this ceremony, and another for that, as though there were a mortall difference betweene them, yea the difference ſo great, that it is ſometimes the greateſt reaſon for one ſide to refuſe this or that becauſe the other uſeth it: Now hee that ſhall ſearch into the innermoſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of theſe antagoniſts, ſhall finde, them that ſo eagerly differ about cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, (who could have beleeved it?) to agree in ſubſtance. Like ſhips that ſail in the ſea a great way aſunder, yet all tending to one haven. All ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this end, to win or obtaine the favour of an angry God. This that hath beene ſpoken may prove a helpe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter a ſpirit of diſcerning unto the ſimple, in theſe diſtracted time, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Commonwealth is not more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted than the Church. Now among ſo many diverſities of opinions, how ſhall we know which is the old and the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19323:31"/>good way, that we may walk in it? One ſaith I am Chriſt, another nay, but I am Chriſt: for thy direction, ſearch for that religion that abaſeth man, that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the glory of grace to God; that propoundeth the free love of God in leſus Chriſt, without mixture of any thing in the creature, that is the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, all the reſt are falſe; that is the true way, and ſtrait line, all the reſt are counterfeit, and crooked. This is the firſt application.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Application is to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our idolatrous thoughts &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that vve have had of God. What fooliſh fancies have poſſeſt our ſoules? How often have we thought God to be like unto our ſelves? How many times have wee imagined an angry God, a wrath full Maieſty? And ſought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe his indignation by faſting, by praying; by almes, by teares, and ſuch like things? O fooliſh man! if his wrath ſhould nor bee before appeaſed, what creature could ſtand in his ſight?
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19323:32"/>Doe wee not ſee when ſome Lion-like man is incenſed, the vvhole houſe trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, not one ſervant, no not a ſon dares come into his preſence, before his wrath be over? If we ſo feare the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt vvrath of man, how terrible would the iuſt vvrath of conſuming fire bee? what great preſumption were it for the creature to come into his preſence, if his wrath were not appeaſed. We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of idolatry crept into our unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Nation. We complain of bowing, of cringing, of croſſing, and many ſuch fopperies. Search we, <hi>I</hi> beſeech you, if idolatry have not hitherto crept into your hearts, if you have not ſet up a great idoll, and bowed unto that image, with all it vvorſhippeth. Learne to make clean the inſide as vvell as the outſide of the cup. Learn to baniſh out of the ſoule thoſe fooliſh and vain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits: learn to ſee the glory of the face of God in Jeſu, and to worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth. There cannot bee greater idolatry committed, than to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19323:32"/>conceive a poſſibility of gaining the love and favour of God, by vvorkes wrought in the creature. This is as great an idoll as that which was ſet up in the plain of <hi>Dura,</hi> in the province of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſixtie cubits high, Dan. 3. This is the Beaſt that hath made the whole earth to partake of her fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>The third Application, is to ſtirre us up to admire the exceeding love of God, and his wonderfull goodneſſe. Heare, O heavens, and give eare, O earth, vvhether ever the like grace were heard of, ſince the mountaines were framed. Who could have expected, that the Lord ſhould have been halfe ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious? Did vve ever imagine to heare ſuch a voyce from heaven to earth, ſo full of grace, ſo full of glory? Had the Lord propounded his love and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation to us, upon hard and difficult conditions, yet if poſſible, ſhould not we have accounted it an happineſſe, for what would not the diſtreſſed ſoul have
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19323:33"/>done, (vvitneſſe the acts of our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers,) for to have purchaſed remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to have obtained the favour of God? But ſee, if any grace bee like to this grace: The Lord calleth from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, unto the ſonnes of men, by his Son Ieſus, ſaying: O yee ſons of men, what could I have done, or what could you have vviſhed me to doe, more then I have done? Behold, I am friends with you, I love you truly; ſee, have I not given you my Sonne? And now <hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you by my Son, that you would bee reconciled unto me; I am friends with you, be you friends with me. Did vve ever think to hear the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to beſeech and intreat us to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto God? That man ſhould intreat God to be reconciled, vvas that vve might imagine; but that vve ſhould find God already reconciled, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of man that he vvould bee reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; this is grace beyond expreſſion. And as this ſets forth the glorious grace of God, ſo doth it aggravate our
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19323:33"/>unthankfulneſſe unto God, if vve ſhall refuſe his gracious offer.</p>
               <p>If ſome poore and baſe man, ſome notorious perſon had offended the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of this Citie, vvhereby he had deſerved ſevere puniſhment, yet the Magiſtrates ſhould ſend for this offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and declare themſelves ſatisfied, and intreat him to ſhake hands with them: If now this offendor ſhould ſtubbornly refuſe to bee reconciled to them whom hee had offended, what ſhould vvee thinke of ſuch a perſon? The caſe is ours, it is wee that have offended God, God hath not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended us; yet now when the offended God ſhall declare his grace, and ſend the miniſtery of reconciliation to us, who were offendors, if wee ſhall now refuſe, and turne away our eares, and refuſe to ſubmit to his righteouſneſſe, what ingratitude will this be? That we may yet more admire the grace of our God, the Lord is pleaſed to uſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar expreſſions, to declare unto us
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19323:34"/>that it pleaſed God to betroath unto himſelfe a wife, whom he would admit into ſo much favour, as to call him <hi>Iſhi,</hi> my Husband, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.16. unto whom he would vouchſafe ſo much honour, as to call her his Spouſe, his Love, his Dove, &amp;c. and to betroath her unto himſelf for ever. Who is it unto whom the Lord vouchſafeth ſuch grace? What perſon is it whom the Lord vvill take to be his Spouſe? Was there ever ſuch a thing as this heard? That povertie ſhould ſue unto riches? That deformity ſhould ſue unto beauty, is no wonder: But that a Mighty, Rich, Beautifull, and Potent Prince, ſhould ſue unto a poore, old, decrepit, defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, diſeaſed, lowſie beggar, what ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry can witneſſe any ſuch thing? And with reverence and trembling be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the mighty God of heaven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troaths unto himſelfe, and ſweares unto vile, poore, deformed, ſinfull, diſeaſed, loathſom man. When man intendeth to take a companion of his love, ſome
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19323:34"/>aime at Nobility, ſome at Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, others at Riches: theſe are the three load-ſtones that commonly attract the liking and love of man: But it is not ſo with God. Look we at the nobility of his Spouſe, at her parentage, from whence ſhe is deſcended; <hi>Thy father was an Ammorite, thy mother a Hittite:</hi> ſhe is baſe borne, a <hi>daughter of whoredoms.</hi> But it may bee beauty might recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence the baſeneſſe of her birth. Look we at her beauty: her native beauty is blood and pollution, a deformed crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; Her artificiall beauty, neither <hi>waſhing nor ſwadling, nor ſalting.</hi> But peradventure, what was lacking in birth and beauty, might be ſupplied in riches and plenty, (for riches make many mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages,) let us ſurvey her riches: Behold, in ſtead of an habitation, <hi>Thou waſt caſt out in the open field:</hi> In ſtead of rayment not wherewithall to buy her <hi>wedding</hi> garments &amp; ornaments, <hi>nakednes,</hi> even <hi>ſtark nakedneſſe, I ſpread the skirt of my clothing over thee, and covered thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.</hi> Here is a Spouſe that hath
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19323:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:19323:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:19323:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:19323:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:19323:37"/>not wherewithall to buy her a <hi>wedding garment.</hi> O the depth of the riches of the mercy of God! Neither noble, nor beautifull, nor rich; and yet the Lord hath ſet his love upon us. Nay, here is one thing exceedeth all this that hath been ſpoken: So miſerable was our condition, that it hath coſt the Lord a great dowry. And the Lord muſt buy us unto himſelf, not with ſilver or gold, nor with 200. fore-skins of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines: but with the pretious blood of the Sonne of God. I deſire to leave you in admiration of this tranſcendent love, and to paſſe unto the fourth Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to comfort the diſtreſſed ſoule.</p>
               <p>Here are the queries of thy burdened ſoule anſwered. What goodneſſe muſt I find in me? What conditions? What qualifications, before that I beleeve God to bee a father to mee in Chriſt? What muſt I doe to bee ſaved? Thou ſeeſt here the freeneſſe of Gods grace, the glory of his reconciliation. And I will bee bold to ſay unto thee, as <hi>Moſes</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:19323:37"/>ſpeaketh unto Iſrael in another caſe, <hi>Stand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord, which he hath ſhewed you this day,</hi> Exod. 14.13. Or as <hi>Iehaziel</hi> ſpeaketh unto Iudah in another caſe. <hi>Ye ſhall not need to fight in this battel, ſet your ſelves, ſtand yee ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord with you, O Iudah, and Ieruſalem,</hi> 2 Chron. 20.17. What ſhall I doe to obtaine the favour of God? I ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve him favourable unto thee, freely for his own ſake. But here the poore ſoule will obiect and ſay, Alas! ſhould I beleeve that have not one iot of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in me; Nay more, that have all manner of evill in me? I anſwer, Thou haſt as much in thee as God requires at thy hands, to precede his love, to goe before his reconciliation. If hee had ſaid he could not love thee before ſuch and ſuch conditions, then thou might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt have had cauſe to diſtruſt his love. But thou haſt ſeen his love to man, even dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes. He came to call ſinners, not righteous
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19323:38"/>to repentance: Come to him empty of all goodneſſe, and partake of his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: come to him hungry, and hee ſhall fill thee; thirſty, and hee ſhall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie thee. O what iniury doe we unto the grace of God, in that wee imagine God to bee like unto ſome niggardly man, who will not bid us welcome to his houſe, unleſſe wee bring our coſt with us: The Lord lookes for nothing at our hands to obtain his favour: come unto him naked, and hee ſhall cloath thee. But the poore ſoule will yet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect further, and ſay: My caſe is yet worſe then you perceive: for I am not onely void of goodneſſe, I am not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly full of filthineſſe and abomination, but which is worſt of all, <hi>I</hi> cannot leave my ſinnes, <hi>I</hi> cannot forſake my whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and drunkenneſſe. How oft have <hi>I</hi> vowed? How oft have <hi>I</hi> promiſed? Yea how oft have <hi>I</hi> ſworne to forſake my ſinnes, and yet all in vain? <hi>I</hi> have returned with the Dogge to the vomit, and with the waſhed Sow, to wallow
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19323:38"/>in the mire? What ſay you to my caſe? If <hi>I</hi> ſhould now come unto Chriſt, would he bid me welcome? If <hi>I</hi> ſhould beleeve God loving unto mee, would it not be the greateſt ſinne unto me? Muſt not <hi>I</hi> forſake and leave my ſinnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>I</hi> beleeve? Muſt not <hi>I</hi> caſt out the rubbiſh out of my ſoule, before Chriſt will love me? Muſt <hi>I</hi> not firſt bee wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and cleanſed, before Chriſt will ſhew any favour unto me. Although the anſwer to this obiection doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belong unto the ſecond thing to be ſhewed; (namely) mans reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God, yet <hi>I</hi> will ſpeak ſomthing. And I deſire thee to try one concluſion, to come unto Chriſt firſt, and leave thy ſinnes afterward; get power from him to forſake thine iniquities. This is the reaſon why thy labour hath been in vaine, becauſe thou haſt gone the wrong way to work, that is, to mortifie thy ſin firſt, and to come to Chriſt afterwards. Now how is it poſſible thou ſhouldeſt mortifie thy ſin before thou beleeveſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19323:39"/>in his name, when <hi>whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin?</hi> Doeſt thou thinke to caſt out rubbiſh without him? Doeſt thou think to bind the ſtrong man by thine own power? Thou art deceived. Woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou mortifie thy ſinne? See the order of the holy Ghoſt <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie therefore your members which are upon the earth, fornication, &amp;c. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, wherefore</hi> ſee verſ. 1. <hi>if yee bee riſen with Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</hi> Firſt riſe with Chriſt, and then mortifie. See the example of <hi>Mary,</hi> who had ſeven divels in her, ſhee doth not ſay, If <hi>I</hi> could caſt out my divels, then <hi>I</hi> would come to Chriſt, but ſhee commeth and bringeth her ſeven divels with her, and the Lord caſteth them our every one for her. Doe thou like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, bring thy ſinnes with thee, and let him caſt them out for thee. If thou ſay, if <hi>I</hi> were waſhed, then <hi>I</hi> could beleeve, then <hi>I</hi> could come boldly to him, <hi>I</hi> aſk thee, who ſhould waſh thee? <hi>I</hi> ſay, come unto him foule, and he ſhall make
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19323:39"/>thee cleane. Doth not hee call <hi>all that labour, and are heavie laden, Math.</hi> 11.28. the burden and load is ſin. He doth not ſay, Lay downe your burden firſt, and then come unto me; but come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me laden, and I will give you reſt.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, is it not written, that <hi>neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate perſons, &amp;c. ſhall inherit the kingdome of God?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10. Againe, is it not written, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holineſſe no man ſhall ſee God,</hi> Heb. 12.14. <hi>To ſee God, and to inherite the kingdome of God,</hi> are nothing elſe, but to beleeve in God, and his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. But this you ſee cannot bee without holineſſe, therefore I muſt have holines firſt, before I can beleeve. I anſwer, the Text ſaith not to, but <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holineſſe no man ſhall ſee God.</hi> If I ſhould ſay, without eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no man can live; wouldſt thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently conclude, that I muſt eate and drinke before I be alive? When ſenſe will tell thee I muſt bee alive, before I
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19323:40"/>can eate and drinke. Yet this is thy ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, Without holineſſe no man ſhall ſee God, therefore we muſt have holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before we can ſee God. When it is evident, we muſt ſee God before wee can have holineſſe: for, <hi>Whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne,</hi> Rom. 14.23. But the meaning of the place is, that Chriſt will not only purge the conſcience, but the converſation alſo of al ſuch as come to him, that is, beleeve in his name, and that a reformed converſation ſhall (though not goe before) yet accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a cleare apprehenſion of the grace of God in Chriſt leſus.</p>
               <p>And thus wee give an anſwer unto that other portion of holy Scripture, Fornicators ſhall not inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of GOD; not that it is to bee thought, that men muſt firſt mortifie their ſinnes, before they can come to the Kingdome of God; but that entring into the Kingdome of God, the Lord would vouchſafe unto them power to reforme their lives. And that this is
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19323:40"/>the true ſenſe of the place, is plaine by the eleventh verſe: <hi>Such were ſome of you, but yee are waſhed, but yee are ſanctified, but yee are juſtified in the name of the Lord Ieſus, and by the ſpirit of our God.</hi> They were ſuch untill they were waſht, and how were they waſht? even <hi>in the name of the Lord Ieſus, and by the ſpirit of our God.</hi> When the buyers and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers had prophaned the Temple, the Lord doth not ſtay while ſome body had caſt them out, and then goe into the Temple afterwards, but he enters into the Temple firſt, and making a ſcourge of ſmall cords, he drove them all out of the Temple, <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.15.</p>
               <p>So fareth it with the Temple of thy body, that is prophaned with ſin, and thy conſcience that is defiled with ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Thou muſt not thinke that thy conſcience muſt bee waſhed firſt, and then the Lord to enter afterwards, but the Lord muſt firſt entor, and waſh thee and purge thee by his blood, which <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the conſcience from dead workes, to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19323:41"/>ſerve the living God,</hi> Heb. 9.14. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou complaineſt, thou canſt not leave thy ſinnes, I ſay, thou hadſt the more need to beleeve in Chriſt, that thou mighteſt have power to forſake them. But poore ſoule, thou doſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect further, and ſay, I have beene an extortioner, a grinder of the faces of the poore, a theefe, a purloyner, and what, ſhal I venture to beleeve in <hi>Chriſt</hi> before I have made reſtitution, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to them whom I have wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged? Are we not taught out of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Non remittitur peccatum, niſi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituatur oblatum;</hi> without reſtitution no remiſſion?</p>
               <p>I anſwer: firſt, there are many things that are well ſpoken by the Fathers, in one ſenſe, which are perverſly applyed in another. This ſentence is true in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of reconciliation of man to man; but not true in reſpect of God to man, or man to God. As when a man ſhall by a lawfull Church bee for extortion excommunicated, the Church ought
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19323:41"/>not to receive him againe untill reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bee made. And thus may wee in good ſenſe underſtand other paſſages of the Fathers, which are otherwiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly applyed by themſelves &amp; others. <hi>Wilt thou deſerve pardon</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>waſh away thy ſinnes by teares.</hi> This is good in my firſt ſence of reconciliation of man to man, as when the Church ſhall excommunicate an offendor, and hee ſhall humble himſelfe with teares in his eyes, he ought again to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But to apply this as a meares to reconcile God to man there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more abominable.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the way, to give thee warning of the groſt applications which are made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Fathers, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> nor what they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> doubt: Thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> uſe thou haſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſay, beleeve firſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> forward: for this, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> beyond all except <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtood forth,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19323:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:19323:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:19323:43"/>and ſaid unto the Lord, <hi>Behold Lord, the halfe of my goods I give to the poore, and if I have taken any thing from any man, by falſe accuſation, I reſtore him fourefold.</hi> If wee looke backe to the ſixth verſe, there wee ſee that <hi>Zacheus</hi> received <hi>Chriſt</hi> ioyfully. <hi>Zacheus</hi> was an <hi>arch-publican,</hi> verſe 2. a man that was a <hi>ſinner,</hi> verſe 7. yet this <hi>ſinner,</hi> this <hi>arch-publican</hi> received Chriſt firſt, (not into his houſe onely, but into his heart alſo) and then he makes reſtitution af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward; goe and doe likewiſe; thou ſeeſt the abundant grace of God: bove and beyond all obſtacles: if thou canſt beleeve, thou needeſt not feare, though thou haſt beene never ſo ſinfull. Thus much for the fourth Application.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Applicat. <hi>5.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The fifth: If God be ſo freely recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to us, how ought we to be eaſie to be intreated to be reconciled one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other? <hi>The Lord ſlow to wrath, and full of compaſsion, and loving kindneſſe.</hi> Take
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19323:43"/>we heed that we bee not full of wrath, and ſlow to compaſſion. God is recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to us before wee aske; how much more ought wee to bee reconciled to thoſe that have offended us, and ſay, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us? Oh that we had ſo much cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in us, as to beare one with another, the ſtronger with the weaker, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy differences might have an end. Secondly, is God thus freely reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to us? Oh let us be intreated to bee reconciled unto him: which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond generall I have to ſhew unto you, <hi>What it is for man to bee reconciled to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19323:44"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19323:44"/>
            <head>RECONCILIATION OF MAN to GOD.</head>
            <byline>By HENRY DENNE.</byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I enter to ſpeake of <hi>Mans reconciliation to God,</hi> It is neceſſary that I premiſe a diſtinction, and ſhew you a two-fold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, ſet out unto us in the Scriptures. 1. <hi>Originall,</hi> 2. <hi>Actuall.</hi> Beare with the termes, I confeſſe they are not altogether ſo fit as I could wiſh: But I therefore thought fit to uſe theſe termes, that I might para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell this diſtinction unto another, uſed by Divines of <hi>Originall</hi> and <hi>Actuall</hi> ſinne. <hi>Originall reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19323:45"/>is wrought without us by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon, yet for us: you may call it the reconciliation of our nature. <hi>Actual reconciliation</hi> is wrought with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, although not by our owne pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. This you may call the reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our perſons or conſciences, the one being the reconciliation of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to God, the other the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that, and the premiſed recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation to our ſoules: That this is not an unneceſſary diſtinction you ſhall find by comparing ſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures together: the firſt is <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>When we were enemies we were reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne.</hi> Againe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.16. <hi>That he might reconcile both unto God into one body by the Croſſe having ſlaine the enmity thereby, Col.</hi> 1.21.12. Thirdly, conſider what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18, 19. <hi>All things are of God who hath reconciled us to himſelfe by Ieſus Chriſt, and hath given unto us the miniſtery of reconciliation: To wit, That God was in Chriſt reconciling the world unto himſelfe, not imputing their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19323:45"/>unto them.</hi> Now compare wee theſe three places forementioned, with that which we find, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, 20. <hi>We are Ambaſſadors for Christ, as though God did beſeech you by us, we pray you in Chriſts ſtead, be yee reconciled unto God:</hi> In the former places the Apoſtle told us wee were reconciled; and in this place, he beſeecheth us to be reconciled. For to take up this difference, I ſay that in the former he ſpeaketh of our <hi>Originall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation,</hi> wherein our nature was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God by Chriſt, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond I ſay, he ſpeaketh of our <hi>Actuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation,</hi> wherein our conſciences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come reconciled to God, through the apprehenſion of the reconciliation which Chriſt hath wrought for us. Firſt of all I muſt ſpeak of our <hi>Originall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation.</hi> And there I lay downe this propoſition, that we were reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne, without any previous conditions in us, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by us. You ſee it is the act of Chriſt upon the Croſſe, it was done by his death: The Lord Chriſt being a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19323:46"/>common perſon, taking our nature up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, <hi>we are ſaid to doe that which he did, and to have that done upon us which was done upon him.</hi> As in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> we all ſinned before we were, or bad committed any Actuall tranſgreſſion: ſo in the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> we were reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>As by one mans diſobedience, many were made ſinners, ſo by the obedience of one, ſhall many be made righteous, Rom.</hi> 5.19. I ſay we are ſaid to doe that which he did, as <hi>to be buried with Chriſt, by baptiſme into death, Rom.</hi> 6.4. We are ſaid to be <hi>crucified with Chriſt, as our old man is crucified with him, Rom.</hi> 6.6. to be dead and alive with him. Reckon yee alſo your ſelves to be dead indeed unto ſinne, but alive unto God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. We are ſaid to be <hi>riſen with him, Coloſſ.</hi> 3.1. which is elegantly ſet forth by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Hoſea,</hi> ſpeaking of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt. He ſpeaketh on this wiſe, <hi>After two dayes he will revive us, and the third day he will raiſe us up, and we ſhall live in his ſight, Hoſe.</hi> 6.2. Yet more,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19323:46"/>we are ſaid to be placed together in <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places with him, Eph.</hi> 2.5.6. This is that which I call Originall reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. Whereby we ſee that not onely God was reconciled unto us, but alſo that our nature was reconciled unto God by the death of his Sonne, without any condition, or qualification wrought in us. Thus much for our Originall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation. Now followes our <hi>Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reconciliation;</hi> to wit, the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods reconciliation to us, and of the reconciliation of our nature to God in Jeſus Chriſt. Here I lay downe this propoſition: <hi>Mans Actuall reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation to God requireth previous conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and qualifications to be wrought in man by the ſpirit of God before man can be Actually reconciled to God, or Gods reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation manifeſted unto him.</hi> Althogh this propoſition need no proofe, in regard that the world ſo far doteth on conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they will hardly admit <hi>God to be reconciled to man,</hi> without performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in man: Surely much leſſe will they thinke it poſſible that <hi>Man ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conciled
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19323:47"/>unto God,</hi> without ſomething wrought in man; yet for our better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding I will ſhew you the proofe of this by certaine texts. As <hi>Except a man be borne of water and of the ſpirit, he cannot enter into the kingdome of God,</hi> Iohn 3.5. <hi>Except a man be borne againe he cannot ſee the kingdome of God,</hi> verſ. 3. To enter into, and to ſee the kingdome of God, is that which I call reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God: to know the favour and love of God towards us in Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires you ſee the condition of being <hi>borne againe of water and of the ſpirit,</hi> which is (not to be baptized as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts would have it) but to have <hi>ſuch fruits and effects of Gods ſpirit wrought in us</hi> as purifie the heart, as water doth the body. Secondly, <hi>except yee eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his bloud, you have no life in you,</hi> Iohn 6.53. Marke I pray you, he doth not ſay, that except yee eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his bloud, yee have no life <hi>in God,</hi> or <hi>in Chriſt;</hi> but yee have no life in you. Now you ſee <hi>we muſt eat
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19323:47"/>the fleſh of Christ, and drinke his bloud, or elſe we can have no life in us.</hi> To eate his fleſh and to drink his bloud, is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in him, to have life in you, is to know Gods favour in Ieſus Chriſt, as much as if he ſhould ſay, except yee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, yee cannot know Gods favour to you in Ieſus Chriſt. Vnto this we may adde in the third place: <hi>Except yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent yee ſhall all likewiſe periſh, Luke</hi> 13.3. And to this place we may alſo referre that place of which we had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſpeake ſomewhat before; <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holineſſe no man ſhall ſee God, Heb.</hi> 12.14. not onely that holineſſe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant or companion of our ſeeing of God, but that <hi>faith</hi> being a part of (yea the firſt fruits of holines) is that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſoule is brought to the ſight of God in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> But I am not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſpend time in larger proofe, though you cannot but perceive I might be very large herein, but I will for your better underſtanding, confine my ſelfe, and goe on to ſhew you in particular, what <hi>Conditions</hi> are required in us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19323:48"/>we can be <hi>reconciled to God.</hi> And here I have occaſion, for the better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of this, to commend unto you three ſorts of conditions,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Antecedent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Preſent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Conſequent.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antecedent Conditions</hi> I call thoſe which are neceſſarily preſuppoſed in us before we can ſubmit unto God, or be reconciled unto him. They are ſuch conditions as may be ſeperated from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation in time, yea they are ſuch conditions, as are, and may be in them which are not reconciled, nor yet ever ſhall be: ſo that they are proper, <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſed non ſolis electis,</hi> to all the elect, but not onely to the elect. 2. <hi>Preſent conditions</hi> I call them, that goe before <hi>reconciliation,</hi> as the cauſe before the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, yet are never ſeperated from recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation in time, but are indeed the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing whereby the holy ſpirit of God doth reconcile man to God. 3. <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent conditions</hi> I call them, which doe alwayes follow reconciliation, as the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19323:48"/>effect the cauſe, although they are inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable in reſpect of time. And I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore undertake to ſpeake of theſe (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the curious may thinke me blame-worthy for tranſgreſſing the rules of method) that we might be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of a rock and ſhelfe; namely, that we doe not confound theſe conditions together, and to take thoſe for <hi>antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> which are onely <hi>conſequent:</hi> which to my knowledge hath made ſome ſouls to make ſhipwrack for a time, when as they would have in them before they beleeve, ſuch conditions as are onely <hi>conſequents,</hi> and not <hi>antecedents</hi> of faith: Firſt, to ſpeake of <hi>Antecedent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> which neceſſarily goe before our <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to God:</hi> They ſhall be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto two heads, the <hi>firſt is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſinne,</hi> with whatſoever is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite unto the <hi>knoweledge of ſinne.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is the <hi>knowledge of the depth of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery by ſinne to be ſuch,</hi> as we can neither help our ſelves, neither is it in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of any other creature for to helpe us: but that we are undone for ever in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19323:49"/>of whatſoever we can doe or any other for us; for untill the ſoule be brought to this, there is no hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling it unto God: for you muſt know, that it is meere neceſsity that drives us: we are by nature <hi>haters of God,</hi> and cannot be brought to come to God in love before we perceive God to love us; ſuch is the malignant nature of man, that if he could make any ſhift in the world, hee would not bee beholding to God for helpe: The prodigall ſonne will never returne to his father ſo long as he can get <hi>cloaths for his backe, and meate for his belly elſewhere;</hi> but when he is brought to that paſſe that he would fain have <hi>filled his belly with husks which the ſwine did eate, and no man gave unto him, Luke</hi> 15.16. Then he is conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to thinke of ſubmitting to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but not before, if he could have got a living by keeping of Hogs, hee would not have returned. Thus is it with man ſo long as he is in any hope to eſcape miſery any other way, there is no hope of his returning to God. <hi>They that be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19323:49"/>whole need not the Phyſitian, but they that are ſick, Mat.</hi> 9.12.</p>
            <p>The Phariſee thinketh himſelf able to eſtabliſh his owne righteouſneſſe: and therefore he will not <hi>ſubmit to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God, Rom.</hi> 10.4. He cares not a pinne for Chriſt, he is whole; he cares not for the Phyſitian. <hi>If any man will come after me, let him deny himſelfe and take up his croſſe daily and follow me, Luke</hi> 9.23. No man can follow Chriſt except he deny himſelfe, his own <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and holineſſe,</hi> would you know a reaſon under the determinate counſell of God; why the Publicans and Harlots received Chriſt, but the holy Phariſees rejected him, (a true paterne of our dayes:) the Phariſees thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves able to ſtand upon their owne legs; they were alive in their conceits, and for them to heare of righteouſneſſe in another, was too great a diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto them and their holineſſe; when the publicans and ſtrumpets, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing convinced of ſinne, and having no righteouſneſſe of their owne, they are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19323:50"/>contented to accept it upon any terms. A rich man, he ſometimes ſcorneth a gift, and ſaith nay, but I will buy it, I will give ſatisfaction for it: but the poor naked man is glad to receive what he wanteth. Thus before the ſoule of man be brought to be reconciled unto God, it is neceſſary that it ſee it ſelfe a <hi>ſinfull creature;</hi> yea ſo ſinfull, <hi>That nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther crying nor howling can waſh it away; yea ſo ſinfull, that no correction or amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life is able to make ſatisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre of the antecedent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: which as I ſaid before, are proper to all; but not onely to them that are reconciled to God: for theſe that I have ſhewed hitherto, may be found in the not reconciled, even as in the recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled: yea, in the reprobate, even as in the elect. The ſecond ſort of conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are preſent, which go before recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, as the cauſe before the effect; but is never ſeparated from it; as being the thing I ſay, whereby the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God doth actually reconcile the ſoule to God. Of this ſort I finde but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19323:50"/>one only condition; namely, of faith, or beleeving. Here are two things to be pondered. The firſt, <hi>That without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, the ſoule (remaining in the body) cannot be reconciled unto God.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, That by beleeving, the ſoule is actually reconciled unto God. For the firſt, it is proved. <hi>He that beleeveth not the Sonne ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him, Iohn</hi> 3.36. To be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God, is to ſee life, therefore he that beleeveth not, ſhall not be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God: but the apprehenſion of the wrath of God ſhall torment his wakened conſcience. He that beleeveth not, ſhall not ſee life; he ſhall ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but wrath. Secondly, <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth not God, hath made him a lyar,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.10. That is, hath accounted him a lyar. Now, who can finde in his heart to be reconciled to a lyar? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is plain, that <hi>without,</hi> or <hi>before faith,</hi> man cannot be reconciled unto God. For the ſecond, that by beleeving, the ſoule becomes to be reconſiled unto God: is proved; <hi>He that hath received
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19323:51"/>his teſtimony, hath ſet to his ſeale that God is true.</hi> John 3.33. <hi>As many as received him, to them he gave power to become the ſonnes of God, even to them that beleeve on his name, Iohn</hi> 1.12. Whoſoever belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, hath power to cry, <hi>Abba</hi> Father. And to this place, we refer that knowne text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Therefore being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And this is the proper office of faith, (as it juſtifieth) <hi>to reconcile the ſoule and conſcience unto God,</hi> and to make us at peace with him, by aſſuring us of his favour and good will towards us, in Jeſus Chriſt, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, in that God gave his only Sonne to be a propitiation for our ſinnes, and to ſatisfie whatſoever the juſtice of God required at his hands. And this is our receiving of Chriſt, our putting on of Chriſt, and our living by faith (if we take faith for beleeving.) And thus much of the ſecond condition which is <hi>preſent:</hi> Now followes the third ſort of conditions, which are conſequent unto our reconciliation, and things that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19323:51"/>our ſalvation. Theſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are firſt, <hi>Ioy in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Love to God and his Church.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>New obedience in newneſſe of ſpirit, and not in oldneſſe of the letter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Ioy in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conſequent, and an inſeparble com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion to our reconciliation by faith; as appears by that which hath been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before, touching joying in belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>with joy unſpeakable and full of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> And indeed, how can it be that it ſhould be otherwiſe: can the men of this world hear of great poſſeſſions fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len unto them, without joyfulneſſe? How then is it poſſible, that the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the living God, can come to the apprehenſion of the fatherly love of God in Chriſt, but they muſt needs <hi>ſing a new ſong, yea, break forth into ſinging, and cry aloud,</hi> with the bleſſed Virgin, ſaying, <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirit hath rejoyced in God my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, Luke</hi> 1.46. If I could this day bring you happy tydings of reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene King and Parliament,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19323:52"/>(which the God of heaven effect,) what joy would this work in the hearts of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man here preſent? How much more ſhall the tydings of eternall peace by Jeſus Chriſt, affect the ſoule with extraordinary comfort. Here what the Lord ſpeaks concerning the new Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>God ſhal wipe away all teares from their eyes, and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, nor crying, &amp;c.</hi> Rev. 21.4. Let others think what they will; I firmely beleeve the <hi>new Ieruſalem,</hi> to be the glorious kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>(which is righteouſneſſe, and peace, and joy in the holy Ghoſt)</hi> advanced in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: and hither alſo are to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thoſe glorious things that are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the City of our God, by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell Prophet, in theſe words, <hi>The ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed of the Lord ſhall returne and come to Sion with ſongs, and everlaſting joy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their heads: they ſhall obtaine joy and gladneſſe, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flye away,</hi> Iſay 35.10. This is the promiſe of our Saviour, <hi>Your ſorrow ſhall be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into joy, Iohn</hi> 16.20. This is the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19323:52"/>of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>To be the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, to ſpeak peace and joy unto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> And therefore amongſt the ſundry precious gifts, which are declared to be the fruits of Gods Spirit, <hi>joy,</hi> is not the leaſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. This alſo is the lot and inheritance of the Saints of God: for wee reade not of any converts in the Scripture, but we alſo read of the joy of Gods Spirit repleniſhing their ſoules: They, (even they) who were pricked in their hearts, and knew not what to doe, doe not <hi>eat their meat with gladneſſe and ſingleneſſe of heart, Acts</hi> 2.46. The Eunuch returneth <hi>rejoycing,</hi> Acts 8.39. <hi>Samarias</hi> converſion cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth great joy in that City, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.8.</p>
            <p>But why do I ſtay on particulars, let us heare the Apoſtle for all; <hi>We alſo joy in God through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, by whom we have now received the attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Rom.</hi> 5.11. <hi>We rejoyce in the hope of the glory of God: And more, we glory in tribulation alſo, Verſe</hi> 2.3. Can the Sun be without her light? can the fire bee without heat? Then alſo may the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19323:53"/>of God, the reconciled to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be without joy and peace in belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. Can a man ſtop the ebbing or flowing of the water? then may the ſoules of the reconciled to God be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of thoſe flouds of comforts, which flow from fountaines of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, into the ſubject of comforts, the ſoules of the people reconciled to God. This is the firſt effect of reconciliation, joy, and peace. The ſecond followes; which is, <hi>Love to God:</hi> Love is alſo an inſeparable conſequent of mans recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation: can man behold the beauty of God, and the glory of his face in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt? And the ſoule not be ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with love. See the love of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God, in that garden of ſweet expreſſions, the Book of <hi>Canticles; Stay me with flagons, comfort me with apples, for I am ſick with love, Cant.</hi> 2.5. The love of the reconciled to God, it is a great love: <hi>Many ſins are forgiven her, for ſhe loved much, Luke</hi> 7. A love ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king great delight and contentment in the object beloved; <hi>My beloved is white
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19323:53"/>and ruddy, the chiefeſt among ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. His head is as the moſt fine gold, his locks are buſhy, and black as a Raven, his mouth is moſt ſweet, he is altogether lovely' Cant.</hi> 5.10. &amp;c. Againe, it is a reſtleſſe love, that canfind no content, can take no reſt (nonot in her bed) if ſhee may not enjoy the preſence of her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved. <hi>By night on my bed I ſought him whom my ſoule loved, I ſought him, but I found him not, I will riſe now and goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the City, &amp;c.</hi> Cant. 3.1.2. That this love is an inſeperable conſequent, a daily companion of mans reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God, will bee plaine, when wee ſhall ſee how the Holy Ghoſt, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing unto us the called of God, ſetteth them forth by <hi>this token of love unto Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God: Eye hath not ſeen, nor eare hath not heard, &amp;c. the things which God hath prepared for them that love him,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.9. <hi>We know that all things work together for good to them that love God, Rom.</hi> 8.28. This ornament of love is like the <hi>garment of divers colours,</hi> with which all the Kings daughters, which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19323:54"/>were Virgins, were apparrelled, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.18. If a Woman bee ſeen in the ſtreets without a party coloured gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is concluded, that ſhe is either none of the Kings daughters, or at leaſt no Virgin: ſo is this ornament of <hi>love</hi> (I ſay) that thing, wherewith all the people of God, reconciled to him, are adorned; if wee ſee a ſoule altogether ſtript of this ornament, we conclude, They are not in the number of Gods people; or at leaſt not reconciled. Therefore the Holy ghoſt concludes; <hi>He that loveth not, knoweth not God,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.8. And as on the affirmative, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth, <hi>Grace be on all them that love our Lord Jeſus Christ, in ſincerity, Eph.</hi> 6.24. So alſo on the negative, <hi>If any man love not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, let him be Anathema Maranatha,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. Thus you ſee the conſequents of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, inſeparably conjoyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſo that no creature ſhall be able to put them aſunder: you have ſeene <hi>Peace to the brethren, and love, with faith from God the Father, and the Lord Jeſus
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19323:54"/>Chriſt, Eph.</hi> 6.23. The third conſquent is <hi>new obedience</hi> in newnes of the ſpirit: As peace, and joy, and love follow, and attend upon faith, ſo is new obedience an attendant of love. <hi>This is the love of God, that wee keep his Commondements,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.3. <hi>If you love me keep my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, Ioh.</hi> 14.15. <hi>If a man love me, he will keep my words,</hi> verſe 23. This is that which I had occaſion to ſpeake of before, that the holy Spirit of God doth not onely cleanſe the conſcience, but in ſome meaſure the converſation alſo: This is that which I ſaid before, <hi>Without holineſſe no man ſhall ſee God, and drunkards ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of God:</hi> I ſay again, that Chriſt entring into the ſoule, ſhall drive out whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is prophane, and draw up the ſoule by the cords of love unto new obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: And to this place we refer hatred of ſinne, love of vertue, a godly ſorrow for tranſgreſſion committed, revenge upon our ſelves, for the things that are paſt, and a jealous care for that which is to come. But of theſe particularly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19323:55"/>I cannot ſpeake; for as <hi>Rome</hi> was not built on a day, ſo neither can it be puld down in an houre (I mean the Doctrine of <hi>Rome.</hi>) And here I would have made an end of ſpeaking of the conſequents of our <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> but that I fear the timorous ſoule will be ready to ſay, In thus ſaying you have filled my heart with ſorrow: The conſequents of our reconciliation being layd downe, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe they are true; but alas, when I caſt an eye back upon mine owne ſoule, I find my joy &amp; comfort little, my love to be leſſe than my joy, and my obedience to be leaſt of all. This, this puts my heart in feare, and makes my ſoule to tremble. I anſwer, what is it that thou feareſt, O thou of little faith? Thou anſwereſt, thou art afraid, that God is not thy God, that hee is not reconciled unto thee: See thy errour, theſe things cannot be ſignes that God is not recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled unto thee; but they are ſignes, that thou art not fully reconciled unto God, but that thy <hi>faith</hi> is weake like the bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſh, that thy <hi>joy</hi> is as little as thy <hi>faith,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19323:55"/>and that thy <hi>love</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> is as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect as thy <hi>joy.</hi> Meaſure not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation of God to thy ſoule, by the perfection of thy obedience: for in ſo doing thou plungeſt thy ſoule into miferable doubts. But ſeeing the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, not of Gods reconciliation to thee, but of thy reconciliation to God, cry thou unto the Throne of grace, Lord increaſe my faith, and make my love and obedience, my joy, and peace, to abound more and more, through the ſpirit of our God, and the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And thus have I now done with the <hi>Antecedent,</hi> the <hi>preſent,</hi> and <hi>conſequent</hi> conditions, of our reconciliation to God. The next thing that I intend is to make <hi>Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath been hitherto mine endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, to declare unto you the miſterie of ſalvation, and to imitate the skilfull Limbner, to give unto every Limbe and part, not onely his due proportion, but alſo his due place, and not to ſet the head where the foot ſhould be, or the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19323:56"/>foot where the head: I may peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to many ſeem guilty, of that crime which was laid againſt the Apoſtle, to turne the world upſide downe, and to place that in the bottome, which others make the top of the building, and to ſet that upon the roofe, which others lay for a foundation: But I ſubmit my ſelfe to the judgement of the word: Conſider we what hath been ſpoken, of Gods reconciliation to us without all conditions; of our reconciliation to God, originall and actuall: and now let us ſee, if theſe dſtinctions be founded (as it is before proved) upon the holy Scriptures, of the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, whether they bee not blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy that make no difference at all between theſe two, but confounding heaven and earth together, the Creature with the Creator, doe moſt abſurdly apply thoſe things which are antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, or cauſes of our reconciliation unto God, to be cauſes of Gods recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation unto us, drawing a vaile before the free grace of God, and keeping the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19323:56"/>ſoule from ſetling upon a ſure founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: The Lord complained of the Prophets of old (the falſe Prophets) that they <hi>pudled the waters with their feet.</hi>) When water is pudled, it is not water; but water and dirt mingled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: In a puddle no man can diſcern whether it be deep or ſhallow: water is Doctrine, pudling is confounding of things together, without diviſion or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration: O that our dayes were free from this complaint! O yee Paſtours of the Lords flock, that feed his heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; Be you contented to beare the word of admonition, from the meaneſt of the ſervants of God. Look back up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the waters, that yee have made the heritage of the Lord to drink: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the paſtures, which you have ſet before them: have you not made the LORDS ſheep become a prey (ſometimes to preſumption, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to deſpaire) by your Doctrine? Have you not made the ſoules of the righteous ſad, and the ſoule of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to rejoyce? Conſider your wayes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19323:57"/>I pray you: Have you not many a time confounded the conditions of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to God, making that to be the caſe, which is the effect, and that to be the effect, which is the cauſe? Let me beſeech you to weigh theſe things, and to endeavour that your Doctrine may be the <hi>light of the World,</hi> that it may be <hi>cleare as the Chriſtall, proceeding from the throne of God, and of the Lamb, Rev.</hi> 22.1. You ſheep of the paſture of the Lord, the God of his inheritance, know, it your duty aptly to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh theſe things in your owne Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that you may enjoy the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the glory, of the grace of God, ſet up in your ſoules, if you ſearch into the reaſon of your many years bondage, of your miſerable doubting, you ſhall finde your diſeaſe, in that which hath been ſpoken, and I hope the remedy al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: The Lord give you underſtanding.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>Application,</hi> may ſhew unto us the difference, between the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, and the not reconciled: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though both may bee objects of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19323:57"/>grace of God, both beloved of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Father: yet ſhall you finde a vaſt difference, if you look either upon their <hi>Converſations,</hi> or their <hi>Conſciences.</hi> The difference of Conſcience is, the not reconciled, have a defiled, and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Conſcience. A Conſcience that is either ſeared, and fitted with Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call careleſneſſe, or at the beſt, ſitting in darkneſſe and the ſhadow of death, ſeeing no light, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.16. when as the conſciences of the reconciled, doe enjoy the light of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the converſation of the people not reconciled, is either a converſation pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with Phariſaicall righteouſneſſe, and blind zeale, (for all zealous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are not reconciled to God) ſeeking to eſtabliſh its owne righteouſneſſe in the ſight of God: or elſe a converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to the courſe of this world, according to the Prince of the power of the ayre; the ſpirit that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the children of diſobedience; A converſation in the luſts of the fleſh,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19323:58"/>fulfilling the deſires of the fleſh, and of the mind, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2, 3.</p>
            <p>The third <hi>Application,</hi> ſheweth us an open doore, for the eaſie underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and plaine reconciliation of many places of Scripture, which ſeem ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding different, as if no way of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling could be found. Let us learne to diſtinguiſh, when God ſpeaketh of his reconciliation to us, and when hee ſpeaketh of our reconciliation to him. Let us learn to diſtinguiſh, between the thing, and the manifeſtation of the thing: the want of which diſtinction, breedeth an horrible confuſion in the interpretation of holy Scripture; To give an inſtance, it is written, <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Yee are all the Children of God by faith in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It is written again, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Becauſe yee are ſonnes, God hath ſent forth the ſpirit of his ſonne into your hearts, crying Abba Father.</hi> In this laſt place, the Holy ghoſt declares ſon-ſhip to be the cauſe of giving the Spirit, as alſo he declareth it to bee an eternall grace of God, communicated unto his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19323:58"/>people, <hi>Having predeſtinated us unto the Adoption of ſonnes, by Ieſus Chriſt, Eph.</hi> 1.5. But then if this be ſo, how are we ſaid to be ſons of God by faith, &amp;c? I anſwer, the one ſpeaketh of the thing it ſelfe, or of Gods reconciliation to us; The other of the manifeſtation of the thing, or our reconciliation to God. Againe, if the grace of adoption be an eternall grace, how is it ſaid, wee are <hi>borne againe by the Word?</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. and <hi>begotten by the Word? Iames</hi> 1.18. I anſwer, theſe places are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the manifeſtation of Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not of the act of Adoption it ſelfe: And that this is ſo, is plaine, <hi>God hath begotten us againe unto a lively hope, by the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt from the dead,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.3. <hi>A lively hope</hi> is the thing, unto which we are begotten. And that it is ordinary in Scripture, to call the manifeſtation of things, by the names of the things themſelves, will be plaine by two places, (I might bring two hundred) the firſt is <hi>Ierem.</hi> 1.10. <hi>I have this day ſet thee over the nations,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19323:59"/>and over the Kingdomes, to root out, to put downe, and to deſtroy, and to throw downe, and to build, and to plant.</hi> How doth poore <hi>Jeremy</hi> deſtroy Nations? Even by declaring the judgements of God in the overthrow of Nations. And thus doth he plant, by declaring the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promiſes of God in the reſtaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Nations.</p>
            <p>The ſecond place is, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.23. <hi>Whoſe ſins ye remit, they are remitted, and whoſe ſins ye retaine, they are retained.</hi> How do the Apoſtles remit and retaine ſinnes, but by declaring Gods gracious remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to every one that beleeveth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But ſome may object and ſay, why doth not the Lord ſpeak in plain terms? I anſwer who art thou that wilt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Lord, and teach him to ſpeak? I anſwer againe, in our Saviours words, when his Diſciples ask the queſtion, Why ſpeakeſt thou unto them in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles? <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.10. His anſwer is, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is given to you to know the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the kingdome of God, but to them it is not given.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19323:59"/>in reſpect of you, that are my people, I need not to ſpeak more plaine; for you (being taught of God) are able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the miſteries of the kingdom. In reſpect of others: I will not ſpeak more plaine, becauſe to them it is not given to underſtand the myſteries of the kingdome. Thus far for the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: I now draw to an end: only I will give you the <hi>Skeleto</hi> or <hi>Map</hi> of that which hath beene delivered in a few words. Conſider we the cauſes of Gods reconciliation, as it ſtands manifeſted to us in Chriſt. Secondly, the cauſes of our reconciliation to God.</p>
            <list>
               <label>Gods reconciliation to us.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Efficient,</hi> Gods love.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Materiall,</hi> Chriſts righteouſneſſe.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Formall,</hi> Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Finall,</hi> Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, mans ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>Our recodciliation to God,</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Efficient,</hi> Principall H. Ghoſt, inſtrumen. tall faith.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall,</hi> Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal,</hi> Apprehenſion of Chriſts righteouſneſs by faith.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> Gods glory, &amp; mans conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:19323:60"/>
            <p> Conſider we the difference of theſe two in their cauſes. The <hi>finall</hi> cauſe of Gods reconciliation to us, is <hi>ſalvation;</hi> the <hi>finall</hi> cauſe of our reconciliation to God is, <hi>conſolation.</hi> The Lord fill you with his Spirit, that the apprehenſion of Gods <hi>ſalvation</hi> may fill you with eternall <hi>conſolation.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19323:60"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
